<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Iesuites gospel: by W. Crashawe, B. of Diuinity and preacher at the Temple</title>
            <author>Crashaw, William, 1572-1626.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1610</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 177 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 55 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A69161</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 6016</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113949</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849177</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849177</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14313</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A69161)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14313)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 779:11, 1549:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Iesuites gospel: by W. Crashawe, B. of Diuinity and preacher at the Temple</title>
                  <author>Crashaw, William, 1572-1626.</author>
                  <author>Scribanius, Carolus, 1561-1629.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 107, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E, [sic] A[llde] for Leonard Becket, and are to be solde at his shop in the Temple nere the church,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1610.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First four words of title are xylographic.</note>
                  <note>This work reprints, translates, and attacks a Latin poem on the Virgin of Halle in "Amphitheatrum honoris" (1606) by C. Bonarscius, a pseudonym of Carolus Scribanius--STC.</note>
                  <note>Variant (earlier state?--STC): with preliminary leaves collating A⁴ a²  including an epistle to the Lower House of Parliament.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The Iesuits gospell.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: pi¹ B-O⁴ P² .</note>
                  <note>Formerly also STC 14533.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 14533 un UMI microfilm reel 1549.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; Bodleian library copy lacks all before page 14 and is cropped affecting text.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the Cambridge University Library and the Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Appears at reels 779 (Cambridge University Library copy) and 1549 (Bodleian Library copy).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mary, --  Blessed Virgin, Saint --  Legends --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Scribanius, Carolus, 1561-1629 --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Jesuits --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14313:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14313:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE IESVITES GOSPEL BY <hi>W. Craſhawe,</hi> B. of Diuinity and Preacher at the Temple.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>E, A.</hi> for <hi>Leonard Becket,</hi> and are to be ſolde at his Shop in the TEMPLE nere the Church. 1610.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:14313:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:14313:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE POINTS OF NEW DIVINITIE CONTAINED IN this Goſpell.</head>
            <list>
               <item>1 THat the Milke of Marye may come into com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon with the blood of Chriſte.</item>
               <item>2 That the Chriſtian mans faith may lawfully take holde of both as well as one.</item>
               <item>3 That the beſt compounde for a ſicke ſoule, is to mixe together her milke and Chriſts blood:</item>
               <item>4 That the ſinnes &amp; ſpirituall deſeaſes of the ſoule are cured as well by her milke as his blood.</item>
               <item>5 That Chriſt is ſtill a little childe in his Mothers armes, and ſo may be prayed vnto.</item>
               <item>6 That her milke and the merit and vertue of it, is more pretious and excellent then Chriſts blood.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:14313:3"/>
               <head>JN THE APPENDIX.</head>
               <item>1 THat no man, but a woman did helpe God in the worke of our redemption.</item>
               <item>2 That God hath made Marye partaker and fellow with him of his diuine Maieſtie and power.</item>
               <item>3 That God hath deuided his Kingdome with Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye, keeping Iuſtice to himſelfe, and yelding Mercy to Her.</item>
               <item>4 That a man may appeale from God to Her.</item>
               <item>5 That a man ſhall oftentimes be ſooner heard at Gods hands in the mediation of Marie, then of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:14313:3"/>
            <head>THE OCCASION OF THIS IESVITICALL BLASPHEMYE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>VSTVS LIPSIVS, a man of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning enough but too much levitye, hauing runne ouer all religions; and at laſt ſet vp his reſt in <hi>Poperye:</hi> fell in his declining and doting dayes to open <hi>Idolatrye:</hi> And as he neuer troubled himſelfe much with Chriſt in his life (whoſe very name a man ſhall ſeldome finde in his bookes) ſo at his end, wanting matter (it ſeemes) to magnifye Chriſt, he writes 2. books in praiſe and honour of 2. Idols: namely 2. old rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, or 2. new forged pictures of a Woman with a Child in her armes. Which muſt needs be taken for pictures of our Ladye: Wherein the prophane wretch bluſheth not to write, that at theſe 2. Images, there are more and greater miracles wrought, then the ſcriptures ſpeake of to be done by Chriſt himſelfe. A learned lowe-Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trye Diuine wondring that ſuch Owles durſt flye abroade at Noone light, and ſuch tromperye be ſet to ſale in theſe daies of knowledge, Wrote a ſhort reproofe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:14313:4"/> of the impietyes, vttered in the firſt of theſe bookes, which is:</p>
            <q>De <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgine Hallenſi.</q>
            <p>Wherein, becauſe the Ieſuits were alſo touched, as being the Fathers of ſuch fooleryes, and the makers of thoſe bolts which ſuch fooles as <hi>Lipſius</hi> do ſhoote: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon a Ieſuite of <hi>Antwerpe</hi> calling himſelfe <hi>Clarus Bonar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcius,</hi> (but his true name being, <hi>Carolus Scribanius</hi>) ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vpon him in a Ieſuiticall pride the generall qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell of the whole order of Ieſuits, vndertakes to defend their Innocencie, and their Honour (forſooth) againſt all the world: and to that end writes a booke, and cals it</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>The great Theater of the Jeſuits Honour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p> Amphitheatrum Honoris.</p>
               <p> In quo Caluiniſtarum in Societatem crimina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones iugulatae.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Wherein, after many blaſphemies againſt Chriſt: ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies &amp; ſclanders againſt Princes: all kinde of lyes againſt our Miniſters, and Profeſſors: he comes at laſt to defend their freind <hi>Lipſius,</hi> and his legend of our Ladye of Hall: And after he hath abuſed him that wrote a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, with all deſpightfull termes, and rayld moſt artificially, wherein he excels all other Ieſuits, (<hi>Parſons</hi> excepted) as far as they, all other Papiſts: He makes a tranſition from rayling on men to playing with God: and from diſgracing Princes to dallying with
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:14313:4"/> Ieſus Chriſt: and not onely defends the legend of <hi>Hall,</hi> Written by <hi>Lypſius,</hi> but further to ſhew his own devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he makes a Poeme, not to the honour of God, or of Chriſt the Mediator, But to our Ladye of <hi>Hall</hi> and the Childe Ieſus. Wherein, whether the verſe be better or the matter worſe is hard to tell: But whether his deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion therein is greater to a Creature, or his blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie againſt the blood of the Mediator, let the Chriſtian Reader Iudge, by the Poeme it ſelfe, which hereafter followeth.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <div xml:lang="lat" type="version">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:14313:5"/>
               <head>EX CLARIBONARSCII AMPHYTHEATRO HONORIS. <hi>Lib.</hi> 3 <hi>Cap.</hi> 8 <hi>pag.</hi> 356. <hi>editionis</hi> 2. 1606. AD DIVAM HALLENSEM, ET PVERVM IESVM.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>AEREO lac inter meditans, inter<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> cruorem<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>Inter delicias vberis, &amp; lateris.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="2">
                  <head>2</head>
                  <l>Et dico, (ſi forte oculos ſuper Vbera tendo)</l>
                  <l>Diua Parens Mamma gaudiapoſco tuae.</l>
                  <l>Sed dico (ſi deinde oculos in vulnera verto)</l>
                  <l>O Ieſu, lateris gaudia malo tui.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="3">
                  <head>3</head>
                  <l>Rem ſcio. Prenſabo, ſi fas erit, Vbera dextrae</l>
                  <l>Laeua prenſabo vulnera, ſi dabitur.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="4">
                  <head>4</head>
                  <l>Lac Matris miſcere volo cum ſanguine nati:</l>
                  <l>Non poſſem Antidoto nobiliore frui.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="5">
                  <head>5</head>
                  <l>Vulnera reſtituent turpem vlceribus mendicum:</l>
                  <l>Teſta cui ſaniem radere ſola poteſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:14313:6"/>
                  <l>Vbera reficient Iſmaelem ſitientem</l>
                  <l>Quem <hi>Sara</hi> non patitur: quem neque nutrit <hi>Agar:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Illa mihi ad peſtem procul &amp; procul expungendam:</l>
                  <l>Iſta mihi ad longas eualitura febres.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="6">
                  <head>6</head>
                  <l>Ira vomit flammas, fumatque libidinis Aetna?</l>
                  <l>Suffocare queo ſanguine, lacte queo.</l>
                  <l>Liuor inexpleta rubigine ſaeuit in artus?</l>
                  <l>Detergere queo lacte, cruore queo.</l>
                  <l>Vanus honos me perpetua prurigine tentat?</l>
                  <l>Exaturare queo ſanguine, lacte queo.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="7">
                  <head>7</head>
                  <l>Ergo Parens &amp; Nate, meis aduertite votis:</l>
                  <l>Lac peto, depereo ſanguinem: vtrumque volo.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="8">
                  <head>8</head>
                  <l>Paruule maternis medius qui ludis in vlnis</l>
                  <l>Qui tua iam comples vbera, iam vacuas:</l>
                  <l>Quid me reſpectas obliqua tuentibus hirquis?</l>
                  <l>Roboris in Coelum nil habet Inuidia.</l>
                  <l>Saepe quidem dixti, noxis offenſus iniquis,</l>
                  <l>Tune meas mammas, Improbe, tune meas?</l>
                  <l>Nolo tuas o nolo tuas Puer auree mammas:</l>
                  <l>Non ſum tam duri, tam grauis oris homo:</l>
                  <l>Sed tantum lateris pluat vnica &amp; vnica ſtilla:</l>
                  <l>Et ſaltem a dextrae vulnere gutta pluat.</l>
                  <l>Si nihilè dextrâ vis impluere, implue laeuâ:</l>
                  <l>Si nihil è laeuâ, de pede ſanguis eat.</l>
                  <l>Si tibi non placeo vulnus mihi vulnera danto:</l>
                  <l>Mercedem danto vulnera, ſi placeo.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="9">
                  <head>9</head>
                  <l>Saepe mihi Babylon patera propinat, &amp; auro,</l>
                  <l>Ingeminatque meis auribus, euge, bibe.</l>
                  <l>Non faciam, vel ſi Coelum miſcebitur Orco,</l>
                  <l>Non faciam, meretrix impia, non faciam.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="10">
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:14313:7"/>
                  <head>10</head>
                  <l>O fitio tamen, o vocem ſit is inter cludit!</l>
                  <l>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>te, <hi>cruore</hi> ſitim comprime, <hi>Lacte</hi> Parens.</l>
                  <l>Dic matri, meus hic frater ſitit, optima Mater,</l>
                  <l>Vis de fonte tuo promere, deque meo?</l>
                  <l>Dic Nato, tuus hic frater, mi mellee fili</l>
                  <l>Captiuus monſtrat vincula, lytron habes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="11">
                  <head>11</head>
                  <l>Ergo redemptorem monſtra te iure vocari</l>
                  <l>Nobilior reliquis ſi tibi <hi>ſanguis</hi> ineſt.</l>
                  <l>Tuque Parens monſtra matrem te iure vocari,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vbera</hi> ſi reliquis diuitiora geris:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="12">
                  <head>12</head>
                  <l>O quando lactabor ab vbere, vulnere paſcar!</l>
                  <l>Delicijſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> fruar, Mamma, latuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> tuis!</l>
                  <l>Parce Deus, magno ſi te clamore fatigem:</l>
                  <l>Non potis Imperio, non potis arte regi.</l>
                  <l>Exagitante ſiti, Patientia perdit habenas.</l>
                  <l>Clamores ſi vis tollere, tolle ſitim.</l>
                  <l>Pluris ego clauis: ſaturaſti ſanguine clauos:</l>
                  <l>Lancea<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> erubuit ſanguine tincta tuo.</l>
                  <l>Pluris ego pannis: madu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>runt vndi<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> panni</l>
                  <l>Nati a vulneribus, Matris ab vberibus.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="eng" type="version">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:14313:5"/>
               <head>TO OVR LADYE OF HALL, <hi>AND</hi> TO THE CHILDE IESVS.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y thoughts are at a ſtand, of Milke and Bloud</l>
                  <l>(Delights of Breſt &amp; ſide) which yeelds moſt good</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="2">
                  <head>2</head>
                  <l>And ſay when on the teares mine eyes I caſte:</l>
                  <l>O Lady, of thy breſt I begge a taſte.</l>
                  <l>But if mine eyes vpon the wounds do glide,</l>
                  <l>then (Ieſu) I had rather ſucke thy ſide.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="3">
                  <head>3</head>
                  <l>Longe haue I muſed, now know I where to reſt</l>
                  <l>for with my right hand I will graſpe the breſt,</l>
                  <l>(If ſo I may praeſume) as for the wounds:</l>
                  <l>With lefte ile catch them: thus my zeale abounds.<note place="margin">A mixture of Chriſts blood and a creatures milke to make vp the confection which muſt heale our ſoules.</note>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="4">
                  <head>4</head>
                  <l>And of the milke, and blood in mixture, make</l>
                  <l>the ſoueraignſt cordiall ſinfull ſoule can take.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="5">
                  <head>5</head>
                  <l>Theſe woundes corrupted vlcers mundifies</l>
                  <l>which none can cure vnleſſe he canterize.</l>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:14313:6"/>
                  <l>Thoſe breſts the faynting <hi>Iſmael</hi> well wold cheriſh</l>
                  <l>whome <hi>Sara</hi> ſcorn'd and <hi>Agar</hi> would not nouriſh:</l>
                  <l>The firſt from me expells all peſtilence:</l>
                  <l>the ſecond driues all lingring feauers hence.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="6">
                  <head>6</head>
                  <l>Doth Ire belch fire, or luſt like Aetna ſmoketh?</l>
                  <l>eyther the <hi>blood</hi> or milke this feruor choketh.<note place="margin">How the blood an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> the milk <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> made equ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Doth enuyes ruſt enroule me round about?</l>
                  <l>this <hi>milke,</hi> or that ſame blood ſoones ſcoures it out.</l>
                  <l>Or do vaine glorious tumor ſtuffe me ſtill</l>
                  <l>Here <hi>blood</hi> and milke inough my thirſt to fill.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="7">
                  <head>7</head>
                  <l>Mother and Sonne giue eare to what I craue:</l>
                  <l>I begge this mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ke, that blood, and both would haue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="8">
                  <head>8</head>
                  <l>Youngling, that in thy mothers armes art playing</l>
                  <l>ſucking hir breſt ſometimes, and ſometime ſtaying:</l>
                  <l>Why doeſt thou veiwe me with that looke of ſcorne?</l>
                  <l>tis forceleſſe enuy that gainſt thee is borne.</l>
                  <l>Oft haſt thou ſayd (being angry at my ſinne)</l>
                  <l>dareſt thou deſire the teates my foode lies in?<note place="margin">Here th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> milke is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uanced <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>boue th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> blood.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>I will not, oh I dare not, golden childe</l>
                  <l>My minde from feare is not ſo farre exilde:</l>
                  <l>But one, euen one poore drop I do implore</l>
                  <l>from thy right hand, or ſide: I aske no more.</l>
                  <l>If neyther; from thy left hand let one fall:</l>
                  <l>Nay from thy foote, rather then none at all.</l>
                  <l>If I diſpleaſe thee let thy woundes me wounde:</l>
                  <l>But pay my wage if I in grace befound.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="9">
                  <head>9</head>
                  <l>Ofte-times doth Babylon in gold me ſend</l>
                  <l>ſtrong wine, and whiſpers to me, drinke my friend.</l>
                  <l>No, no, though heauen and hell ſhould make confuſion</l>
                  <l>Ile none falſe ſtrumpet, hence with thime illuſion.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="10">
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:14313:7"/>
                  <head>10</head>
                  <l>But ah, I thriſt: ah drought my breath doth ſmother!</l>
                  <l>Quench me with <hi>blood</hi> ſweet Sonne, with <hi>milke</hi> good Mother.</l>
                  <l>Say to thy Mother, ſee my brothers thirſt,</l>
                  <l>Mother, your <hi>milke</hi> will eaſe him at the firſt.</l>
                  <l>Say to thy Sonne, Behold thy brothers bands,</l>
                  <l>ſweete Sonne, thou haſt his ranſome in thy hands.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="11">
                  <head>11</head>
                  <l>Shew thy redeeming power to ſoules oppreſt:</l>
                  <l>thou Sonne, if that thy <hi>blood</hi> excell the reſt.</l>
                  <l>And ſhew thy ſelfe iuſtly ſo ſtil'd indeede,</l>
                  <l>thou Mother, if thy <hi>breſts</hi> the reſt exceede.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="12">
                  <head>12</head>
                  <l>Ah when ſhall I with theſe be ſatisfide?</l>
                  <l>When ſhall I ſwimme in ioyes of breſt and ſide?</l>
                  <l>Pardon (o God) mine eager earneſtnes:</l>
                  <l>if I thy lawes, and reaſons bounds tranſgreſſe.</l>
                  <l>Where thirſt ore ſwayes, pacience is thruſt awaye:</l>
                  <l>ſtay but my thirſt and then my cries will ſtaye.</l>
                  <l>I am better then thy nayles: yet did a ſtreame</l>
                  <l>of thy deare <hi>blood</hi> waſh both the Launce and them</l>
                  <l>More worthy I then clouts: yet them a flood</l>
                  <l>moyſtned of Mothers milke, and of Sonnes blood.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="approbation">
            <pb facs="tcp:14313:8"/>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:14313:8"/>
            <head>THE APPROBATION OF THIS AVTHOR.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>LARVS Bonarſcius, otherwiſe called <hi>Carolus Scribanius</hi> is a Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuite now liuing at Antwerpe, and of much account amongſt them; he wrote this booke and ſpewd this blaſphemy out of his vncleane heart ſome 4. or 5. yeares agoe. And whereas both the Author and his booke deſerued the fire or halter, It was ſo farre from being miſliked in the Romiſhe Synagogue, or any waye cenſured, that ſince then the book hath beene reprinted and the Author and his booke ſtande inrolled, aproued and commended (in their great volumes ſet out for that purpoſe) for good and Catholicke.</p>
            <q>Clari Bornaſcij Amphitheatrum Honoris Ieſuitici, in quo Caluiniſtarum in ſocietatem Ieſu crimina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones iugulatae:<note place="margin">Palaeopoli hoc eſt Antu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erpia.</note> proſtant Palaeopoli <hi>1605.</hi> &amp; poſtea <hi>1606.</hi> Haec Poſſeuinus Ieſuita in Appararu ſacro Tom. <hi>1.</hi> lit. C. pag. <hi>357.</hi> editionis vltimae.</q>
            <p>And it is to be noted that theſe volumes of Poſſeui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne containe onely an inrollment and approbation of
<pb facs="tcp:14313:9"/> no writers at all, ſaue ſuch as are approued Romiſh Catholicks: and are ſet out with great and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke allowance of the Romiſhe ſtate, as may be ſeene at the beginning of the firſt Tome.</p>
            <p>Beſides, let all men knowe the book ſtands yet vncenſured, and the man liues ſtill vnpuniſhed, nay vnreproued, or rather comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded and rewarded for it: therfore this cannot be calld an obſcure or pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate facte, but may properly be held the fact of the Romiſh Church or State.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:14313:9"/>
            <head>A DISCOVRSE OF THE LADIES OF HALL AND SI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHEM, IN WAY OF PRE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face: ſhewing particularly <hi>the occaſion of this new</hi> Goſpell.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He bleſſed <hi>Mother of our Lord,</hi> as the Church in all ages hath done, ſo doth ours, willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly honour, as the moſt bleſſed of all Saints, yet as a creature, and as one ſaued by <hi>her ſonne,</hi> that <hi>Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our in whome her ſpirit reioyced:</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">Luke 2</note> we know and acknowledge that not ſhe but the <hi>holy ghoſt</hi> hath ſaid that <hi>all generations ſhal cal her</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">Luke</note> 
               <hi>bleſſed:</hi> Yet we muſt confeſſe, we are of that fathers religion, who ſaid,<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <p>Auguſt lib. de virginit</p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>elicior par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus ſpiritualis quam carnalis beatior enim Maria fuit con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cipiend. Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum fide qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> carne mater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na enim pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinquitas nihil ei profuiſset niſi felicius chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tum corde qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> carne geſtaſset</p>
               </note> 
               <hi>her ſpirituall bearing of Chriſt was happier then her
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:14313:10"/> carnall,</hi> and <hi>her ſelfe more bleſſed by conceiuing Chriſt in her heart then in her wombe, and by beleeuing in him then by bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring him, for her bearing him in her body would not haue ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued her ſoule, if ſhe had not more happily borne him in her heart.</hi> And in another place,<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <p>Idem inde felix quia verbum dei cu ſtodivit non quia in illa ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bum caro fact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um eſt. Papiſts them<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelues cannot deny but our men do (out of this caſe) ſpeak and write moſt reuerently of the bleſsed virgin as nam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, Luther O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecolampadius Brentius ſpan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genbergius vrb Rheg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s Bucer Bullin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</p>
                  <p>All this is confeſsed by Coccius the great Papiſt, in his theſaure cathelico.</p>
                  <p>To. 1. Li. 3. 21. 5. p. 300.</p>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſhe was happy and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, not becauſe in her the word was made fleſh, but becauſe ſhe heard the word of God and kept it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This her bleſſednes, farre be it from vs to impeach: and who would not yeild her all bleſſednes and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour that a creature may haue, of whome <hi>God</hi> vouchſafed to take the fleſh of <hi>man?</hi> And if any of our Religion hath giuen any words of her, that may giue the leaſt blemiſh to her bleſſed ſtate, it was not done in any the leaſt <hi>contempt</hi> of <hi>her,</hi> but in the <hi>zeale</hi> they bare to the honour of their <hi>Sauiour,</hi> whome they held diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honoured by the vnequal co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paring of her with him: for what will not a Chriſtian mans zeale cauſe him to doe, when he ſeeth his God diſhonoured? who would haue thought that <hi>Moſes</hi> would haue caſt ſo careleſly out of his hands, ſo pretious a iewell as were the two Tables written with the finger of God? and yet when he heard the name of the <hi>Lord</hi> blaſphemed, he forgot himſelfe and them, and as though he remembred <hi>none but God,</hi> he threw them away and brake them in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
            <p>if <hi>Moſes</hi> his zeale makes his haſtines excuſable then no reaſon to condemne them whoſe zeale gaue paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage to their paſſions, and cauſed them for the honor of the <hi>Creator</hi> to forget the priuiledge of a <hi>Creature:</hi> and I dare ſay there neuer was learned man of our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:14313:10"/> that preſumed to touch the very skirt of the garment of her glory, vnleſſe they ſaw her ſet in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon with <hi>God</hi> or <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> which ſeeing the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Church dare offer to do, thereby ecclipſing the glory of <hi>Gods mercy</hi> and the worthyneſſe of <hi>Chriſts ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfaction,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bonauenture</hi> himſelfe ſaid, that we muſt take heed leaſt we ſo farre aduance the glorye of the mother that we diminiſh the glorye of the ſonne.</note> we holde it our dutyes to be zealous for the glory of our God, and to preſerue as farre as in vs ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the prorogatiues of our Sauiour, if it be ſaid that they match her not with God or <hi>Chriſt.</hi> I anſwer they doe, and that in ſuch a meaſure, as we dare pronounce her or any Angel <hi>accurſed</hi> that ſhould either arrogate or accept of that which the Romiſh religion aſcribes vnto her. Too good euidence hereof hath beene ſeene in all ages for theſe 200. yeares laſt paſt, wherein they haue fallen from honoring her as a <hi>Saint,</hi> to magnifie her as a <hi>Mediator;</hi> to pray to her as to a <hi>God,</hi> to truſt in her as in a <hi>Sauiour:</hi> Many perticulars haue beene ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified by many of <hi>our writers</hi> which by the <hi>aduerſaries</hi> could neuer be <hi>denied</hi> (they are ſo euident) &amp; yet were they neither <hi>recanted</hi> nor <hi>remoued,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reinoldus de Idolatria. Catalogus te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtium veritaetis. Perkins, <hi>of the Idolatrye of the laſt times.</hi>
               </note> but contrarywiſe they haue proceeded from euil to worſe, till their blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy haue euen peirced the <hi>heauens</hi> and touched the Crowne of the <hi>Almighty,</hi> &amp; confronted the woundes, merrits and bloud of our <hi>Sauiour.</hi> Particular inſtances heereof are many, which may be collected out of the Authors of late yeares, part whereof ſhall if God permit be perticularized in this Treatiſe.</p>
            <p>But aboue all there is one, which as it is the lateſt, ſo is it the fowleſt, and wherein Popiſh blaſphemye is at the height, as now it giues hope to all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:14313:11"/> men that their prayers are heard, her end is at hande,<note place="margin">Reuel.</note> and that <hi>her iniquitie is come vp before God.</hi> And there remaines nothing but the reuenging hand of God to be ſtretched out vppon her. We haue it not from the report of merchants, from the letters of the poſts, nor from the Intelligence of Embaſſadors, for then our aduerſaries might ſuſpect it, Nor from the reporte or writings of our own men, for then let the world not beleeue vs: but we haue it from the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it ſelfe euen from the <hi>Recorde</hi> wherein it is written, with the <hi>Authors</hi> hand: and ſurely if the eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence were not beyonde exception, our ſelues would not beleeue it of them, though they be our enemies. Thus ſtandeth the caſe.</p>
            <p>Amongſt the late deuices that Romiſhe pollicye hath forged to vpholde their hierarchye, a principall is, their <hi>art of Miracles,</hi> which they pretende to haue ſo ordinarye,<note place="margin">In 80. the Pope loſt all England Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Ireland, Denmarke, Sweden and a great part of Germany, France, Swit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zerland, Peland, and Hungary.</note> that in many Churches they haue more <hi>miracles</hi> then <hi>ſermons:</hi> but alas daily experience ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth that they be <hi>lyinge Wonders</hi> and no true miracles. Now becauſe ſuch tricks are moſt effectuall to delude the common people, and that they finde themſelues and their cauſe to haue loſt much of late in many parts of <hi>Chriſtendome,</hi> therefore to recouer themſelues and to gaine credit to their forlorne cauſe, they haue moſt buſily applyed this point of late, and haue by the crafte of Machiauelian <hi>Ieſuits</hi> (as <hi>Watſon</hi> their bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Preiſt often ſtiles them) ſo farre preuailed,<note place="margin">In their quod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libets often.</note> that there ſcarce paſſeth a month wherin ſome new Image of our Lady is not found, or ſome ſtrange miracle and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:14313:11"/> wonders heard of.</p>
            <p>Two yeares agoe they cauſed a ſtorye to be written and publiſhed wherein they bluſh not to make their people beleeue, that more miracles,<note place="margin">See the booke called <hi>Iuſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tii</hi> diua. <hi>virgo Hallen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis.</hi>
               </note> and greater then Chriſt did, haue beene and are daily done at <hi>Hall</hi> (a towne in the borders of <hi>Brabant</hi> and <hi>Henault</hi>) by the virgin Mary at a picture of hers in a Chappell there: and this is ſet out by no vulgar or triuiall fellow, but by that famous Apoſtat <hi>Lipſius,</hi> that the tale may carry the more credit: and the miracles are not of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary but of the higheſt nature: for healing of fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, feuers, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uulſions, is nothing, nay:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>airus daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</note> ſight is giuen to the blinde, and whereas Chriſt raiſed but 3 from the dead (that we know of) our Lady of <hi>Hall</hi> (ſaith <hi>Lipſius</hi>) gaue life to 7 at leaſt that wer dead: Loe here how far ſhort Chriſt himſelfe is of his mother:<note place="margin">Omnia quafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit Chriſtus fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit Franc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſcus plura quam fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit Chriſtus fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit Franciſcus. lib. conformit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum beati Fran<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciſci.</note> and now we meruaile no more if they haue written that <hi>St. Francis did all that Chriſt did and more then Chriſt did,</hi> ſeeing the picture of his mother, can doe more then he did.</p>
            <p>I ſay the picture of his mother, becauſe <hi>Georgius fabri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius,</hi> the Popes ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſor of books, in his allowance of this legend of <hi>Lipſius</hi> ſaith, that God giueth and commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicateth downe power to worke miracles not onely to the <hi>virgin Mary</hi> and the <hi>Saints,</hi> but euen to their I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages or pictures: beholde good reader a worthy peice of new refined popery, <hi>Gods diuine power is communicated to the very pictures of creatures:</hi>
               <note place="margin">ſtrange doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</note> And if a y man obiect that miracles are not in theſe dayes to be expected, <hi>Lipſius</hi> hath a learned and catholike anſwer,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:14313:12"/> that now indeede in reſpect of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or to auerre his doctrine, or to maintaine his honour, they neede not, but the caſe is otherwiſe (ſaith he) with <hi>Saints,</hi> for many doe refuſe to worſhip them, and grudge at the honour that in the Romiſh Church is giuen them,<note place="margin">By popiſhe doctrine Chriſt doth more to eſtabliſhe the worſhipping ot Saints then his owne.</note> and therefore to defend them in this point, and to eſtab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh that worſhip which they doe vnto them, God ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth ſo many miracles to be done euen by their <hi>Images:</hi> which anſwere being well conſidered of, what a kinde of doctrine it containeth, I leaue to the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and iudicious Reader:</p>
            <p>I onely ſay, that if this be true, then how ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth it with the very body and current of his ſtory, by which no man can deny, but it is apparent that moſt of the miracles which he ſpecifieth, were done almoſt 200. yeares agoe, namely betwixt the yeares 1400. &amp; 1500. long before <hi>Luther</hi> began to preach, and as they ſay afore our Religion was in the world, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently before the worſhipping of Saints was with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, therefore it followeth; that miracles were ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary at Saints Images, euen then when worſhipping of Saints was not denied: <hi>Lipſius</hi> might haue done well to haue reconciled ſo euident a contradiction.</p>
            <p>But what aſſurance haue we for the truth of theſe miracles? or how know we that this is an approued picture of our Lady? <hi>Lipſius</hi> anſwereth that there was one <hi>Sophia</hi> daughter to the <hi>Landgraue of Heſſe,</hi> by his Lady Saint <hi>Elizabeth:</hi> (a Saint of Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the 9. making within foure yeares after her death.)</p>
            <p>This <hi>Sophia</hi> (ſaith he) as it is thought, had certaine I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:14313:12"/> of our Lady, giuen her by her mother <hi>Elizabeth</hi> (was it then but thought ſo, and muſt we now beleeue it?) one of theſe ſhe gaue to the Nunnes of the Nunry at Vilvord, and that was called <hi>our Lady of comfort:</hi> 2 more ſhe gaue to <hi>Madam Machtild,</hi> or <hi>Maud</hi> her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands ſiſter, who beſtowed them thus: one ſhe gaue to <hi>Graueſand,</hi> another to <hi>Harlem</hi> (two townes in <hi>Holland</hi>) the third, (which it ſeemes ſtole all the vertue from both the other) to <hi>Hall,</hi> a towne in <hi>Henalt,</hi> (and this is that we now ſpeake of:) and to ad more credit to the ſtory, he tels vs that this Lady <hi>Maude</hi> was Mother to that Ladye <hi>Mawde</hi> who bare at one birthe 364. chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, which were all borne aliue,<note place="margin">An olde ſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye but greatly ſuſpected by <hi>Eraſmus</hi> and other learned men, to be fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bulous.</note> and baptized by a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop: So (ſaith <hi>Lipſius</hi>) this is that image, which now we worſhip at <hi>Hall:</hi> and thus ſtrong a foundation hath the ſtorie: and now may not all <hi>Caluiniſts</hi> be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed to doubt of this ſtorye or to ſuſpect theſe grounds?</p>
            <p>Now therefore ſurely we muſt needs beleeue (els we are vnbeleuing heretikes) that one was before this Image diſpoſſeſſed of a diuell without any other meanes, for ſo he ſaith, &amp; that ten at leaſt were deliue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> preſent death by but calling or thinking vpon <hi>our Ladye at Hall,</hi> and that ſeauen were raiſed from death to life being but layd before the image; and all theſe within the ſpace of xx. yeares, and in one countrye (ſo ordinarye a matter is it in Poperye to raiſe the dead.) Nay we muſt beleeue (or els we are infidels) that when a faulkener ſhould haue beene ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged for looſing his Lords faulkon, and had the rope about his necke,<note place="margin">An excellen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and new foun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> way for faul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ners to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e their loſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>kes, neuer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ore heard prooue this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſius and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u wilt haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ny Faulke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rs turne pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ts.</note>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:14313:13"/> and did but call to mind the <hi>Ladye of Hall,</hi> forthwith the Hawke came flynge home againe, and light vppon the faulkeners ſhoulder, and ſo ſaued his life: for this is not <hi>Lipſius</hi> aſhamed to report. Which if it be true, then we ſhall leſſe wonder hereafter at that in the <hi>legende,</hi> where it is reported how a Parrat hauing gott abroad out of her cage and ſporting her ſelfe in the ayre, was by and by eſpied by a hawke, who being readye to ſeaze vppon her, Inſtantly the <hi>Parrat</hi> ſeing herſelfe in danger to be ſurprized, cried out <hi>S. Thomas a Becket</hi> ſaue me: and preſently the hawke fell downe dead and the <hi>Parrat</hi> was deliuered.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ee the booke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alled, <hi>Liber <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>onformitatum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Franciſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f any impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion.</note>As alſo thoſe miracles of <hi>S. Francis</hi> ſo far beyonde <hi>Chriſts</hi> or his Apoſtles, that he tamed wilde beaſts, that he preacht vnto a <hi>Wolfe,</hi> and conuerted him from his crueltie, and calling him by the name of his brother <hi>Wolfe,</hi> made the towne of <hi>Engubium</hi> &amp; him friends, who of long time had beene at contention, and for the aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the peace, he made his brother <hi>Wolfe</hi> to giue him his faith in the Market place, before the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, and afterward the <hi>Wolfe</hi> went vp and downe the citye, and tooke his meat from dore to dore: Loe here you heretikes, here is a Miracle worth ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: and if they wil not beleeue me, looke in the holy booke of Conformities,<note place="margin">See the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitye of the olde im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsion and his life in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh.</note> and there you ſhall finde all this and much more: as namely, how the birds would come flyng, and the beaſts flocking about him to heare him preache, and how the Nightingales and other birds would come and helpe him to ſay Maſſe, and ſing his office, and would anſwere him verſe for verſe.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:14313:13"/> Come out ye heretikes <hi>(Caluiniſts and Lutherans) Saint.</hi> Francis and his followers challenge you all to bring out one miracle like theſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sedulius</hi> a Po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>piſhe writer hath this la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> yeare defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded all theſe.</note> to approue your religion ſurely they may, and for ought I ſee <hi>Chriſt and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles</hi> alſo, for they neuer wrought ſuch a miracle to confirme the Goſpel. Is it not then apparant that ſaint Francis hath done more then Chriſt did?</p>
            <p>Oh my deare countrymen (you that name your ſelues the catholikes of England) if you would but o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen your eyes and conſider of this, I durſt make your ſelues iudges, what diuinitie this is: if you ſuſpect me, beleeue me not, looke into the bookes them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and beleeue your owne eyes: if you ſay vnto me that ſome ſuch impieties and follies might creepe into the olde bookes, 100. or 200. yeares agoe when the times were not ſo warye nor ſuſpitious; but the Church hath ſince reformed ſuch abuſes, I anſwere, I alledge moſt of this out of the Booke of co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mityes, lately corrected and printed in Italye within theſe 20 yeares: but if you looke into the olde one, printed 100 yeares agoe, (wherewith your forefathers were abuſed) you ſhall there finde ſuch matter, a for reuerence of the Reader <hi>I ſhame,</hi> and for the honour of <hi>God</hi> I <hi>feare</hi> to write.</p>
            <p>And as for theſe miracles at our Ladyes picture at <hi>Hall</hi> they were neuer offred to the worlds view nor e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer came to light till within theſe 3 yeares that <hi>Lipſius</hi> (a man who durſt doe any thing but honour Chriſt) preſumed to publiſh them, and with foule impiety to write that in theſe dayes <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his doctrine, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:14313:14"/> and religion needes no miracles but the Saints and their ſeruice and worſhip do ſtand in neede there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: and as in the infancy of the Church <hi>Chriſt</hi> had his, ſo in the perfect ſtate of it, <hi>Saints</hi> and their Images muſt haue their miracles:<note place="margin">See the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>olde impreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or his life in Engliſh.</note> but obſerue withall that (if they ſay true) more ſtrange and as I may ſo ſay, more <hi>Miraculous Miracles</hi> are done for the honour of <hi>Saints,</hi> and approuing the worſhipping of them and their I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, then were for the eſtabliſhing of the Goſpell, the abrogating of the ceremoniall law, &amp; for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing <hi>Chriſt</hi> to be the ſonne of God.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lipſius</hi> died a relapſed papiſt at <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ucin</hi> ano.</note>If <hi>Lipſius</hi> were liuing I would not ſpare to tell him: that this his doctrine ſmels ſtrongly of that whereof he hath beene, (it ſeemes not without cauſe) ſuſpected, which becauſe he is dead I will forbeare to name.</p>
            <p>But ſome of our Engliſh Papiſts (which are not learned) may doubt whether there be ſuch a booke or no, or if it be not deuiſed by vs, and fathered on them, (for ſo do their Preiſts often ſuggeſt vnto them of ſuch books as they feare the people will miſlike) but if any of their miſleaders doe ſo miſinforme them, let them know the booke hath beene twiſe printed at <hi>Antwerpe,</hi> &amp; once at <hi>Paris,</hi> with allowance of authoritye in both places, not onely of the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of Books, and the Archbiſhop of the place, but the matter and miracles in the book are confirmed with the bulls of 2. Popes,<note place="margin">Theſe bulls of 2. Popes are in the end of the book.</note> one of Pope <hi>Nicholas,</hi> in the yeare 1451. the other of Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the 8. within theſe 8. yeares: and if any ſhould be ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable as to thinke that we haue forged all this,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:14313:14"/> 
               <hi>Poſſeuine the Ieſuite</hi> may giue him full ſatisfaction: who in his <hi>Apparatus ſacer</hi> hath publiſhed to the world that <hi>Lipſius</hi> in the yeare and at the place aforenamed,<note place="margin">Iuſtus Lip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius vir vere Catholicus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter complures eruditiſſimos libros, anno. 604 edidit li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brum hac prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notatione Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti Lipſii diua virgo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>allen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis eius<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficia &amp; mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cula bona fide at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ordine deſcripta. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuerpia apud moretum. Poſſe. Appa. ſa To. 2. in litera I. page 318</note> did put out ſuch a worke, &amp; giues him ſpetiall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>menda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for his labours, in that and the like for the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like cauſe.</p>
            <p>But hath not <hi>Lipſius</hi> recanted, or the Romiſh Church reformed this ſince then? Alas, <hi>Lipſius</hi> was ſo farre from that, that the yeare after, very neere vnto his death, as though he intended nothing but <hi>to heape vp wrath againſt the day of wrath,</hi> he added <hi>drunkennes to thirſt,</hi> as the Prophet ſaith, for heaping ſin vpon ſin, in ſtead of reuoking &amp; recanting his former colluſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he publiſhed another pamphlet, a more ridiculous Legend, and fraught with more improbabillities and impoſſibilities then the former. It beares this title: <hi>Iuſtus Lipſius his hiſtory of our Lady of Sichem, or of our La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies picture, of the craggy-rocke or ſharpe hill,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iuſti lipſii diua virgo A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpricollis.</note> 
               <hi>and of her new miracles and benefites: at Antwerpe.</hi> 1605.</p>
            <p>At this Image ſaith he, are wroght miracles of al ſorts Apoplexis, Epilepſies, goutes and all kinde of diſeaſes are healed, lame are reſtored to limbes, blind to ſight, deafe to their hearing: and all theſe by heapes, not ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome or extraordinarily, but yearely monthly, dayly: almoſt 60. are regiſtred by <hi>Lipſius</hi> beſides many more omitted, and all to be done in 2. or 3. yeres, inſomuch as if his report be true, God makes miracles farr more ordinary for the honour of Saints and their Images, then he did for confirming the doctrine of Chriſt and his Apoſtles: But what credit hath the ſtory of our
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:14313:15"/> Lady of <hi>Sichem?</hi> euen as good as hath our Lady of Hall, els let the reader iudge.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The tale of the Image of the eragg ye hill.</note>Neere to the little poore (but olde) towne of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chem</hi> ſaith <hi>Lipſius,</hi> there is a mount, barren, rough, and craggy, on one ſide whereof there is a little hillocke: on it growes an Oake, and in it or faſtened to it, is a lit-Image of our Lady, which hath done great miracles in time paſt, and was therefore worſhipped of the people there: but how is that proued? thus: aboue 100 yeares agoe, a <hi>Shepheard</hi> found that Image, &amp; put it in his boſome, thinking to carry it home to worſhip it, but as he was in theſe thoughts, he was ſodainly ſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken &amp; aſtoniſht in his ſences, &amp; benu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>med in his whole body, inſomuch as he could not ſtirre one foot but ſtood ſtil like a dead tronk, not knowing what to think of it, nor how to help himſelf: his M. wanting both his ſhepheard and his ſheepe, ſought them, &amp; found him ſo ſtanding, who tolde him the whole matter: his M. taking the Image, went with great deuotion and ſet it vp in the Oake againe, &amp; forthwith the ſhepheard had his limbs reſtored, &amp; went &amp; worſhipped it, and ſo by their reports, al the country heard of it, who came by heaps &amp; wer healed of al diſeaſes, but agues eſpecially, and ſo it continued (ſaith he) til within theſe 20. yeres, about which time the bleſſed Image was ſtolne or loſt no man can tell how. (But is it not ſtrange that if it could doe theſe miracles, they would let it be loſt ſo careleſly?) well, loſt it was: But what tho? people went as faſt then as afore, and ſtill as great cures were there done as when the Image was there: and in
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:14313:15"/> want of the Image the people worſhiped the Oake, &amp; why might they not ſaid <hi>Lipſius?</hi> the holy Image had hallowed the tree, ſo that it might lawfully be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped: (heholde popiſh deuotion!) yet ſaith he we worſhipped not the tree, but in it the Image, and in it our Lady, and in her God. Marke good Reader, God gets his worſhip at laſt, thogh it be at the fourth hand: they tender it to the tree, the tree yeeldes it to the <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage,</hi> the Image conueies it to our <hi>Lady,</hi> and ſhe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents it to <hi>God:</hi> ſo then by popiſh doctrine &amp; deuotion God is ſerued and honoured after his creatures, and ſo at laſt gets his owne, If they ſay that the worſhip is intended to God, and is not ended but in him: I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, but were it not better that the worſhip were offered immediately from the heart and hands of the worſhipper to God himſelfe, and to paſſe through no hands, but of his ſonne the mediator? but this is here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, let it paſſe, or els it muſt paſſe the fire.</p>
            <p>To returne to the ſtory: our Lady of <hi>Sichem</hi> is loſt, but what then, muſt the poore towne looſe her traffick and liuing? (nay rather we wil make another, for that is no hard nor vnuſuall thing in that religion:) and ſo ſaith he 7. yeres after: an honeſt and deuout Alderman of <hi>Sichem</hi> (perceyuing well how his and his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours gaines came in, and how the poore towne liued) like a good towneſman, made another Image, put it in a boxe of wood, and faſtened the boxe to the Oake, that ſo their Lady might not be loſt ſo careleſly as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            <p>This new Image thus made, did as many miracles
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:14313:16"/> as the other, <hi>and why ſhould it not, for was it not as good as the other?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Alwaies re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred that I meane not in any of theſe ſpeeches the bleſſed virgin vvhome as I hold a bleſſed Saint in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, ſo I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent her with all the honour that may be giuen to a crea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture: But I meane <hi>Lipſius</hi> his lady of Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chem, or our lady of Hall.</note> 
               <hi>nay it may be it was more curiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly carued and better wrought.</hi> Thus it continued cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thine yeares till at laſt the Pariſh Prieſt perceyuing they began to be well cuſtomed, beſtowed ſome coſt on their Lady which got them ſo much, and built her a little chappell of boords, and there placed her. But ſtill their cuſtome growing greater, they ſhewed them ſelues thankefull to their patroneſſe, and as ſhe fild their purſes, they ſought her honour, and built her a faire chappell of ſtone, ſome 2. yeares agoe, and in that reſteth the Image, working miracles euery day. <hi>But what became of the holy Oake?</hi> it was ſo cut away by pieces by deuout perſons, and carried away, that it was in danger of falling, and a counſell was called in the towne what were to be done with it <hi>(as in ſo great a matter it is requiſite)</hi> and there, after ſerious conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, it was grauely concluded, that it ſhould be cut vp by the rootes, &amp; with much ſolemnity brought into the towne of Sichem, where when it came, forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with happy was he that could get a peece of the holy wood, whereof (ſaith <hi>Lipſius,</hi> and bluſheth not to write it) diuers made them little Images, and with much piety do worſhip them: others that were ſicke of grieuous diſeaſes, ſhaued it into their drinke and drunke it, and ſo were healed. See what an excellent religion this is: one Image hath begot many, and the firſt Image being but faſtened to the tree, ſo ſanctified the whole Oake, that euery Image made of the whole tree, ſhould be as good as it ſelfe, and euery crumme
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:14313:16"/> of the wood ſhould worke miracles, as faſt as the Image did.</p>
            <p>Loe heere the hiſtory of our Lady of <hi>Sichem,</hi> or of the ſharp hil: &amp; this lege<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d is not <hi>Lipſius</hi> aſhamed to thruſt vpon the vvorld, for a true &amp; vndoubted ſtory: ſuch are the times we be fallen into, that to ſet faſt the crowne vpon the Popes head, truth muſt ſtand aſide and lies muſt paſt for currant without controule: and ſuch a cauſe is Popery as cannot continue in credit before the people, but by forging a continued ſucceſſion of lying wonders, for now we are made beleeue, that the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> hath 2. Images within few miles together which haue done more miracles in a fewe yeares by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſt, then God himſelfe did in the olde, or Chriſt and his Apoſtles in the new teſtament: Such Idols of indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation doth the Romiſh harlot aduance againſt the ſoueraigne maieſty of God, to prouoke him withall: for what is it but an Idoll of indignation, that not a creature only, but the very Image of a creature ſhould be made pertaker of the deuine power and maieſty of God?</p>
            <p>The time was when <hi>Iſaiah</hi> the Prophet durſt ſay of God, <hi>I am the Lord, this is my name,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 42.28</note> 
               <hi>and my glory I will not giue vnto another, nor my praiſe to grauen Images:</hi> but how ſoeuer that might be tollerable doctrine in thoſe daies had he liued in theſe, he muſt haue bene taught that a part of the glory and praiſe of God, may daily be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to grauen Images, and yet the glory of God not at all thereby impeached, but rather augmented: Loe what Idols of indignation and abhominations lye hid
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:14313:17"/> vnder this miſtery of iniquity.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Ezech.</note>And yet good Reader (as God ſaith vnto the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet) <hi>turne thee a little</hi> and <hi>thou ſhalt ſee greater abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions then theſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is yet ſcarce 3 yeares agoe ſince the tale of our Lady of <hi>Hall,</hi> was forged by ſome Ieſuit, and publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>Lipſius,</hi> when withall, a faire picture grauen in braſſe was prefixed vpon the firſt page before the booke of <hi>our Lady holding her Sonne in her armes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And beholde, the Ieſuits as though the Mother were a woman and the Sonne but an Infant: or as though they had gained mercy by Chriſt already, and would now ſee what they could get by the Mother, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to call in queſtion his <hi>merits</hi> and mediation, and the dignity of his <hi>wounds</hi> and ſufferings, &amp; at laſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce that his <hi>wounds</hi> and her <hi>paps,</hi> his <hi>blood</hi> and her milke, are either all one, or els that the <hi>milke is better.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet before we enter into the perticular, let the reader obſerue, that though the Image be both of our Lady (as they call her) and of her ſonne Ieſus our Lord, yet notwithſtanding the miracles are all aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed <hi>to her</hi> and her picture, and none to <hi>Ieſus Chriſt:</hi> for the colouring of which impiety, what they can ſay I ſee not, vnleſſe they dare affirme that the ſonne will doe no miracles in the preſence of his mother, to which end, it may well be noted, that generally in all places where the mother and the ſonne, the virgin Mary, and our <hi>Lord Ieſus</hi> be pictured together in their Churches, ſhe is alwaies ſet forth as a woman and a mother, and he as a childe and infant, either in her
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:14313:17"/> armes or in her hand, that ſo the common people might haue occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to imagine, that looke what pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of ouerruling and commaunding the <hi>Mother</hi> hath ouer her <hi>little childe,</hi> the ſame hath <hi>ſhe</hi> ouer her ſonne Ieſus: and that ſeeing the ſonne is but an infant in his mothers armes, therefore they might not wonder why her picture doth all the miracles, &amp; his none; for its likely, Chriſt did no miracles whilſt he was a child: into theſe ſuperſtitious and euen blaſphemous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits do they indeuour to driue their people, not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring what they derogate from Chriſt, ſo they giue it to their Saints: Is it not admirable that ſtill they will make him an infant, ſtill in his mothers armes, ſtill vnder her power, and ſtill all miracles muſt be wrought by her, and at her picture, as though either he could not, or in his mothers preſence would not, or (at the leaſt) as though ſhe had many enemies, and therefore needed miracles, and Chriſt none? But alas who ſeeth not that the Athiſme and prophaneſſe of the world cauſeth euen the name and religion of Chriſt to be blaſphemed, that if miracles might law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully be expected, we ſhould thinke them as needfull as euer ſince the firſt planting of the Goſpell: it is therefore a ſtrange peice of Popiſh doctrine, that there is more cauſe that the virgin Mary and her pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſhould haue miracles for them, then Chriſt and his religion.</p>
            <p>But yet this, and all other their ſuſpicious and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious ſpeeches and practiſes againſt the honour of Chriſt &amp; his religion, are in my iudgement inferiour,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:14313:18"/> and may all ſtoupe to this newe impiety of the <hi>Ieſuits,</hi> wherby the <hi>Mother</hi> is compared to the <hi>Sonne,</hi> not as being a childe, or a man, but as the Sauiour and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator: and the pappes of a <hi>Woman</hi> equalled with the <hi>wounds</hi> of our <hi>Lord,</hi> and her <hi>milke</hi> with his <hi>bloud.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If this were written by <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> ſome might ſay we might report partially, or if it were a matter of olde, the age might yeild ſuſpition that it were made worſe in the carriage: But when it is a matter of ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterday and comes from themſelues, partiallity it ſelfe cannot cauill againſt it.</p>
            <p>And the perticular is this <hi>Clarus Bonarſcius</hi> a Ieſuit or the Ieſuits Patron, publiſhed this preſent yeare to the world a volume large enough, in defence of the whole order of Ieſuits, the booke bears this title.</p>
            <q>
               <p>CLARI BONARSCII, AMPHITHEATRVM HONORIS.</p>
               <p>In quo <hi>CALVINISTARVM IN SOCIETATEM IESV, criminationes iugulatae.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Editio altera, libro quarto auctior. PALAEOPOLI ADVATICORVM, Apud ALEXANDRVM VERHEIDON. 1606.</p>
            </q>
            <p>This volume he erected, as a theater, yea an <hi>Amphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theater
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:14313:18"/> of Honour,</hi> in defence of the Ieſuits, wherein af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had aſſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed with much ſleight of wit, and in a ſtrange ſtile, to wipe away many foule blots, with which that Atheiſticall broode hath ſtained the <hi>holy name of Ieſus,</hi> and adorned it ſelfe (for generally that which diſhonors God adornes them) and after he had ranged ouer al the reformed Churches, and raked vp all rotten ſlaunders, and reuiued the callumniations that were anſwered, dead and buried, 40. 50. and 60. yeares agoe, and rayled vpon the liuing and dead <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin, Beza, Pareus Stenius, Toſſanus, Faius,</hi> and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther holy and learned men, with that bitterneſſe and virulency as neuer was before him: yea, moreouer after that he had laid high and horrible imputations vpon this whole ſtate, and (like a true Ieſuits Impe) ſlaundered the whole gouernement, with foule iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and monſtrous cruelty in many perticulars,<note place="margin">ſee for theſe perticulars of our Queene and ſtate. lib.</note> and had in Ieſuiticall pride, dared to defile the name and honour of renowned Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> (whoſe me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory for euer will be bleſſed) with words vnworthy the mouth of a man (if he were not a Ieſuit:) at laſt from the defence of Ieſuits, he falls in to defend <hi>Lipſius,</hi> (a good friend of theirs) and his two ſtories of our Lady of <hi>Hall,</hi> and our <hi>Lady of the craggy Rocke,</hi> and not onely labours to make good all his fancies and fables, but further (to ſhew that a Ieſuit hath one tricke of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety beyond all, and is anointed by the diuell with the oyle of miſchiefe aboue al his fellowes) addeth a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of verſes directed to that picture, which he calleth <hi>our Lady of Hall,</hi> fraught with ſo fearefull blaſphemies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:14313:19"/> the <hi>blood</hi> and <hi>merits</hi> of the <hi>Mediator,</hi> as no Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian eares to this day did euer heare, and doubtles no Chriſtian heart can patiently endure: and certainely if the bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> to whoſe picture he hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated them, may be his Iudge, without doubt both he and his blaſphemy will be condemned to hell:<note place="margin">Luke.</note> and ſhe <hi>whoſe ſoule reioyced in God her Sonne and Sauiour,</hi> her ſoule I ſay will reioyce in the iuſt damnation of him who ſhal match the milk of her a <hi>creature,</hi> with the blood of him her <hi>Sauiour:</hi> But ſhall we heare them? no will ſome ſay, let blaſphemy rather be buried in the depth of obliuion, darken not the <hi>Sunne,</hi> defile not the <hi>heauens,</hi> poyſon not the <hi>ayre</hi> burden not the earth with it, amaze not the <hi>mindes,</hi> and terrifie not the <hi>conſciences</hi> of weake Chriſtians: and aſſuredly could I <hi>bury</hi> it ſo that it might neuer <hi>liue,</hi> and <hi>quench</hi> it ſo as it might ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer <hi>flame</hi> againe, and if my Booke were the onely Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie in the world, I would rather chooſe to couer this ſhame of the ſhameleſſe <hi>whore of Babilon,</hi> then by diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering it to cauſe good mens <hi>eares</hi> to tingle, and their hearts to tremble: But ſeeing the ſtrumpet hath the whores forehead, and glorieth in her owne ſhame, &amp; founded out this blaſphemy (as with a trumpet) in the eares of all Chriſtendome by publiſhing it in a booke which he calls <hi>the great theater of the Ieſuits Honour,</hi> euen bringing ſo feareful blaſphemy vpon the ſtage, &amp; dare diuulge it in a ſecond impreſſion, leaſt the worlde ſhould want it;</p>
            <p>Let vs therefore craue leaue of our <hi>Lord Ieſus,</hi> to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer her ſhame wherein ſhe glorieth, and that wee
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:14313:19"/> may without impeachment of his honour, repeate ſo foul blaſphemie, that ſo the world may both perceiue what a religion popery is, and that we for our parts <hi>haue no fellowſhip with ſuch abhominable workes of darknes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The title he giues them is this:
<q>Ad Diuam Hallenſem, &amp; Puerum Ieſum.</q>
            </p>
            <p>THAT IS,
<q>To our Lady of Hall, and The Childe Ieſus.</q>
            </p>
            <p>See firſt the impiety lurking in this title. She is a <hi>Queene</hi> or Lady, Ieſus a <hi>Childe</hi> or infant: compare this with holy ſcriptures, they indeede ſpeake both of him and her, but of him as God and a Sauiour, of her as a creature; the mother onely of his humanity (although the mother of him that was God) and exerciſing pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er onely ouer his humanity, and that onely during his infancy and priuatenes, but not after he tooke vpon him the Propheticall office of the mediator,<note place="margin">Iohn. 2.4.</note> for then he ſaid (in a certaine caſe) <hi>woman what haue I to doe with thee?</hi> and againe, being tolde <hi>ſhee was without to ſpeake
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:14313:20"/> with him,</hi> hee anſwered that hee had more Mothers, tho not in the ſame,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ath. 12. <hi>V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t.</hi>
               </note> yet in a better ſence: for <hi>whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer did the will of his father, the ſame ſaith he is my mother:</hi> thus the ſcripture proceeds to deſcribe him in his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheticall, and afterward in his prieſtly office, and leaues him not till at laſt he be aſcended into heauen, and haue taken poſſeſſion of his kingdome, and then the ſcripture leaues him in his glory.</p>
            <p>Is all this true? and yet muſt he now after 1606. yeres be an infant in his mothers armes? and for her the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſcriptures ſpeak no more of her, but as of a creature, a woman, a beleeuing Iewe, a holy ſaint, ſaued by faith in her ſauiour Ieſus Chriſt, and ſo leaues her, with lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle mention (after <hi>Chriſt</hi> was baptiſed, and entred his propheticall office) her <hi>body</hi> to goe the way of all fleſh, and her ſoule to enter into that great glory which Chriſt had purchaſed for her, and all that ſpirituall kindred of his, whome with his owne mouth he had pronounced <hi>more bleſsed</hi> for <hi>hearing his word and keeping it,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 12</note> then they could haue beene by being the mother of his fleſh:</p>
            <p>And yet now after 1600. yeares, ſhe muſt ſtill be a commaunding mother, and muſt ſhew <hi>her authority ouer him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Monſtra te eſſe Matrem ſumat per te preces.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>ſo are the miſſals, Breuia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries &amp; offices that are refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.</p>
               </note> and he <hi>muſt receiue our prayers by her meanes,</hi> and ſtil ſhe muſt beare him in her armes, or lead him in her hand, and her picture muſt worke all the miracles, but his none: and ſhe muſt be ſaluted as a Lady, a Queene, a Goddeſſe, and he as a childe: If this be not ſo, let this Title iudge: <hi>Ad Diuam Hallenſem, &amp; puerum Ieſum.</hi> But let vs leaue the Title, and not ſtand long at the <hi>gates,</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:14313:20"/> but enter this <hi>Citty</hi> of confuſion.</p>
            <p>And now all good Chriſtians hearken with griefe of heart to that which I rather wiſh you might neuer haue heard; but if your eares tingle, your haire ſtand vp, and your hearts tremble at the blaſphemy follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, blame the heart that indighted it, the hand that wrote it, the Religion that allowes it, and not the pen that diſcouers it.</p>
            <p>Thus then begins the Ieſuits Goſpell.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Haereo</hi> lac <hi>inter meditans interque cruore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inter delicias</hi> Vberis <hi>et</hi> Lateris.</head>
               <p>That is:
<q>
                     <l>My thoughts are at a ſtand of <hi>Milke</hi> and <hi>Blood:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>delights of breſt &amp; ſide, which yeilds moſt good.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Earken thou bleſsed Apoſtle</hi> Paul, (if thou in heauen canſt heare the blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my on earth,<note place="margin">11. Cor. 2.2.</note>) thou that didſt preach and write, that <hi>thou deſiredſt to know nothing but Ieſus Chriſt &amp; him crucified:</hi> thou that didſt teach the Churches onely to know &amp; beleeue in <hi>Chriſt</hi> for ſaluation: &amp; almoſt 20 times in thy <hi>Epiſtles</hi> haſt magnified his <hi>Blood,</hi> without once mencioning the virgin <hi>Mary</hi> or her <hi>Milke.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Heare and be aſtoniſhed at this, that ſome who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:14313:21"/> to be thy Diſciples or thy fellowes rather, cannot tell whether to chooſe that <hi>bloud</hi> of the mediator, or the <hi>milke</hi> of a woman: At leaſt harken thou <hi>bleſſed ſpirit</hi> of truth, thou that canſt and wilt heare, thou that didſt inſpire thoſe holy truths into that holy <hi>Apoſtle:</hi> behold a religion riſen vp in the world, that dare compare the <hi>bloud of that God</hi> who was by thee conceiued, with the <hi>milke of that woman,</hi> who was the mother of his humanity and was ſaued from hell and damnation by that bloud, and that dare allow her profeſſors to make doubt whether to eſteeme the greater delight of their ſoules <hi>her milke</hi> or <hi>his bloud:</hi> and we for repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing this, muſt be accounted heretickes: heare from heauen we beſeech thee and Iudge betwixt vs.</p>
               <p>The blaſphemer proceedeth.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Et dico ſi forte oculos ad <hi>Vbera</hi> tendo</l>
                  <l>Diua Parens. <hi>Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mae</hi> gaudia poſco tuae</l>
                  <l>Sed dico ſideinde oculos ad <hi>Vulnera</hi> verto</l>
                  <l>O Ieſu <hi>Lateris</hi> gaudia malo tuae.</l>
               </q>
               <p>That is:
<q>
                     <l>And ſay aloud when I the <hi>Teates</hi> do ſee,</l>
                     <l>O Goddeſſe mother, lend thy <hi>Brests</hi> to mee!</l>
                     <l>But thus I beg, when on the <hi>wounds</hi> I thinke</l>
                     <l>O Ieſu giue me from thy <hi>ſide</hi> to drinke,</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:14313:21"/>
               <p>What before he deliuered more darkely, now he maketh plainer: if any doubt what milke what blood he meant, hee anſwereth our Ladies <hi>Milke,</hi> and <hi>Ieſus Chriſt his blood:</hi> but what, doth popery make queſtion whether of theſe two is better? is this their holy Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Romane faith? If not, let their words be Iudge, I ſtand muſing ſaith he and cannot tel whether to take, milke or blood: <hi>If I looke at her paps, then I long for milke, If to his ſides, then I would haue blood.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Marke how indifferent a papiſt is, whether he receiue the one or the other: is not this euill enough? a man would thinke ſo, yet hearken what followeth, and we ſhall heare worſe: but let vs do it with feare and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of that glorious name, and pretious blood which are blaſphemed.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Rem ſcio, prenſabo ſi fas erit <hi>vbera</hi> dextra</l>
                  <l>Laeua prenſabo <hi>vulnera</hi> ſi dabitur.</l>
               </q>
               <p>in Engliſh thus,
<q>
                     <l>Long haue I muſ'd, now know I where to reſt,</l>
                     <l>for with my right hand I will graſpe the breſt:</l>
                     <l>(If ſo I may preſume) as for the wounds,</l>
                     <l>with left Ile catch them, thus my zeale abounds.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Hetherto he doubted, now he is reſolued: but ſuch a doubt, and ſuch a reſolution, Chriſtian eares neuer heard of: he doubted whether were better, the <hi>blood</hi> of God, or the <hi>Milke</hi> of a creature (the diuell himſelfe
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:14313:22"/> neuer doubted hereof) but now what is his reſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, doth it make amend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>? yes doubtles as the Pope vſeth to make <hi>Chriſt</hi> amends, when he hath diſhonored him: I was at a ſtand (ſaith he) whether to take, and now I reſolue I will haue both: both are ſo good I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe neither, her <hi>milke</hi> his <hi>bloud</hi> both ſo precious, both ſo powerfull, both ſo vertuous, as I will haue both. Both are good, and ſo good as hardly can I finde diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, but if there be any, it is that the <hi>milke</hi> is more excellent, and therefore with my <hi>right hand,</hi> I will make it ſure mine, if I may be ſo bolde as to touch it, or if it be lawful for a ſinners ſoule to taſte ſo glorious, ſo vnualuable and deuine a liquor as is the <hi>Milke</hi> of the <hi>Mother:</hi> and as for the <hi>childe</hi> it is well for him if he may follow his <hi>Mother,</hi> and haue the next place to her: therefore if he pleaſe to giue me leaue I will lay holde with my left hand on his <hi>wounds.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O glorious God, the eternall ſonne of the eternall Father, thou bleſſed Ieſus <hi>Chriſt</hi> the ſtay &amp; comfort of all Chriſtian ſoules, heare in heauen thine holy ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation this hainous blaſphemy, and iudge thy owne cauſe: And if it fal out that any contagion of ſin catch holde on me the writer or any the readers hereof, by not trembling or not ſufficiently deteſting ſuch fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full impiety as this that is paſt or that that is to come: vouchſafe in mercy to forgiue it, and to waſh it away with that moſt precious bloud of thine, whereto all the creatures in the world are not worthy to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared:</p>
               <p>And though this that's paſt, be abhominable, yet
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:14313:22"/> with reuerence to thy holy name and pretious blood, giue vs leaue to diſcouer the height of their iniquity, which ſtill goeth forward in more horrible &amp; feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full manner: for thus ſinges the Ieſuit.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Lac</hi> Matris miſcere volo cum ſanguine nati</l>
                  <l>Non poſſum Antidoti nobiliore frui</l>
               </q>
               <p>that is,
<q>
                     <l>And of her <hi>Milke</hi> mixt with his <hi>blood</hi> Ile make,</l>
                     <l>The ſoueraignſt Cordiall ſinfull ſoule can take.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>So now <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> ſhall haue ſatiſfaction, if there were a fault afore, for if he complaine that the <hi>mother</hi> of his fleſh, a woman and a creature, haue the right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand when <hi>himſelfe</hi> and his merits muſt take the left or none, heere they will make him amends, for that he may haue no cauſe to complaine, for want of place or precedence, her milke and his blood will he mingle both together, and ſo make a ſoueraigne compound cordiall for his ſoule. But what? a mixture of <hi>milke and blood,</hi> of the blood of <hi>God</hi> with the milke of a <hi>crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture?</hi> and is now the blood of the <hi>Lambe of God</hi> but one of the ſimples in that cordiall Antidote, that muſt both reſtore and preſerue the life of mans ſoule? <hi>ye hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens be aſtonied at this,</hi> ſo may we well ſay, for ſo ſaid the Prophet at a matter of farre leſſe wonder, hearken O Chriſtendome, and al ye people, nations, &amp; languages
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:14313:23"/> to whome the bleſſed name of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> hath ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: that poore <hi>paſchall Lambe</hi> of the Iewes that was but a ſhadowe of our Sauiour, the ſigne and ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and in ſome ſort the meanes and inſtrument of the Iſraelites temporall preſeruation, might not, nay needed not to haue any thing mingled with the blood thereof,<note place="margin">Exodus. 12.5. &amp;c.</note> but the <hi>blood</hi> alone being <hi>ſprinckled on their dores</hi> deliuered them from the ſtroke of the deſtroying An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel: this was their paſſouer, &amp; ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Chriſt our paſſouer is ſacrificed for vs:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 5.7.</note> ſhall this then be true, of their paſſouer, a lambe taken out of the fold &amp; flock, &amp; onely dedicated by Gods inſtitution, and ſhall not the blood of our paſſeouer the Lambe of God, God and man Ieſus Chriſt (whoſe Godhead is conſubſtantiall and coequall with the father, and his humanity perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally and indiuiſibly vnited to the deity) being <hi>ſprinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kled on our hearts &amp; ſoules,</hi> ſuffice to preſerue them from the infernall ſtroake of hell and damnation, vnleſſe it be mingled with the <hi>milke</hi> of a creature? pardon this blaſphemy O bleſſed Ieſus Chriſt, if it be not a blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy againſt the holy Ghoſt, and a deſpighting of the ſpirit of grace: pardon it in as many of them as do not ſinne vnpardonably, for thy mercies ſake. Amen.</p>
               <p>But ſay (I pray thee) tell vs in good earneſt, (If ſo we may preſume to call a Ieſuites proctor to his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere) is there not a more ſoueraigne Antidote for a ſinful ſoule, then a mixture &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pound of <hi>Maries</hi> milk and Chriſt his <hi>blood?</hi> then tel vs who can make this mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture? who hath the skill ſufficient for this confection? who giues the true <hi>doſſe?</hi> who apointes the <hi>quantities,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:14313:23"/> Mithridats</hi> and <hi>triacles</hi> for the body are not compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for euery <hi>conceit,</hi> nor matters for euery hand to make, but rather beſeeming the skilfulleſt, and require the ouerviewing eye of the whole Colledge of Phiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſhall then the heauenly Antidote of the ſoule be compounded without a heauenly Phiſition? ſay then (Man) if thou dare ſtand to thy deedes, who was the Phiſition that preſcribed and gaue thee this receipt, was it <hi>God the father,</hi> the fountaine of holineſſe and happineſſe? himſelfe ſaith no, for thus proclaimed he twiſe from heauen of Ieſus Chriſt, <hi>This is my welbelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſonne in whome I am well pleaſed:</hi> In none as in him,<note place="margin">Math. 3. At his bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme: &amp;c. Math. 17 At his tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figuration.</note> nay in none, no not in his mother, but in, for, and by him. Thus the father of heauen hath teſtified that the blood of his ſonne is one ſufficient &amp; ſoueraigne ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, for a heauenly Methridate. Now ſhew thou, (and take the Pope to helpe thee) where euer he teſtified ſo much of her milke: but if no ſuch thing, nay nothing at all, then he was not the Phiſition that preſcribed this mixture.</p>
               <p>Who then, was it Chriſt himſelfe the ſonne of God and the ſonne of this woman? No, for of himſelfe he ſaith, <hi>My fleſh is</hi> (ſpirituall) <hi>meate indeede,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn. 6.</note> and <hi>my blood is</hi> (heauenly) <hi>drinke indeede:</hi> but of her he ſaith that euery true beleeuing Chriſtian,<note place="margin">Matb. 12.4.6.</note> 
                  <hi>is his mother</hi> (as well as ſhe) in the beſt ſence, and much more then ſhe, had ſhee beene no more but the mother of his fleſh: ſurely then if this be a lawfull mixture, which this papiſt makes, the ſonne was much to blame to ſay ſo much of his owne <hi>blood,</hi> that it is <hi>drinke indeed,</hi> and that it giues
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:14313:24"/> the <hi>drinkers eternall life,</hi> &amp;c. and not one word of his mothers milke: Not a word ſayd I? I recall that, for when once a certain woman hearing him preach, not for any thing ſhe ſaw in her, but for the powerfull and <hi>gratious words,</hi> that came from him, would haue had her <hi>wombe bleſſed that bare him,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke. 11.27.28.</note> 
                  <hi>and her paps that gaue him ſucke:</hi> (the worſt whereof is better then her milke) he inſtantly anſwered her, <hi>that much more bleſſed was euery man that heard Gods word and kept it.</hi> If no extraordinary bleſſednes belong to the wombe that bare him (in that reſpect onely, becauſe it bare him carnally) If none to the <hi>wombe</hi> nor <hi>paps,</hi> which ſhal endure for euer, then how much leſſe to the <hi>milke</hi> that fed him, which is va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed &amp; ſhall be no more: If Chriſt would not match her <hi>wombe</hi> or <hi>paps</hi> with a man that feared God, what will he ſay to them that make <hi>her milke</hi> a match for <hi>his owne blood,</hi> the milke being a matter farre inferiour, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to wombe or paps. Thus they may ſee that Chriſt is not a fit Phiſition to make this mixture.</p>
               <p>What then, was the holy Ghoſt the Phiſition that framed this receipt?</p>
               <p>No, for he by his deuine power, conceiued Chriſt in that holy and miraculous maner, that Chriſt was fully without originall ſin, and therefore his blood might well be a pure and perfect ſimple to make the <hi>Aqua Caeleſtis</hi> that muſt quicken dead ſoules: let them approue as much of her if they can, they ſpeake and write that ſhe was conceiued without ſinne originall, and haue a holy day for it, but they can not prooue it: it is an Article of our faith, and grounded on plaine
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:14313:24"/> wordes of Scipture,<note place="margin">Learned Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts hold that the Popes Buls and the decree of the counſell of Baſil do not conclude it as an article of faith.</note> that Chriſt was conceiued without ſinne: and though the whore of Babilon, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme as much of her, yet was ſhe yet neuer ſo impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, as to conclude it an article of the faith. Thus God the father, the ſonne, and the holy Ghoſt, doe all diſclaime the compoſition of this Antidote, as nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther preſcribed nor allowed by them.</p>
               <p>Who then may be imagined to be this Phiſition, was it <hi>Moſes?</hi> no,<note place="margin">Exodus. 12.</note> for he allowed nothing to be ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with the blood of the paſcall Lambe: was it <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaias?</hi> no, for he auoucheth that <hi>with his ſtripes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſay. 53</note> 
                  <hi>are wee healed,</hi> and his ſtripes were not without blood.</p>
               <p>Was it <hi>Zacharia?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Zacha. 9.11.</note> no for he teacheth that <hi>the Church is ſaued by the blood of her couenant,</hi> which is grounded onely on the <hi>Meſſias.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If any other Prophet, let them ſhew him: was it <hi>Iohn Baptiſt:</hi> no for he teſtified that not the mother of his Lord, but his Lord Ieſus Chriſt was <hi>that Lambe of God that takes away the ſinnes of the Worlde.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1.29.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Was it St. <hi>Paul?</hi> no for he teacheth the <hi>Romaines,</hi> that <hi>we are iuſtified freely by his blood:</hi> (beholde yee <hi>Romaniſts,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ro. 3.24.25.</note> theres no milke) and the <hi>Epheſians</hi> that <hi>we haue redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion through his blood:</hi> yet there is no milke,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2, 13. Coloſſ. 1.14.</note> and the <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſsians,</hi> that <hi>he ſet vs at peace through the blood of his croſſe</hi> not the <hi>milke</hi> of her paps:<note place="margin">Hebrews 9.12</note> and the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> that not with any milke, but <hi>with his owne blood he obtained eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall redemption for vs:</hi> to conclude, 13. times at leaſt in his Epiſtles doth he mention the blood of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to the ſame purpoſe, and with the ſame honour as afore, &amp; not once did he ſo much as name our Ladies <hi>milke:</hi> ſurely either this was an intollerable omiſſion in Saint
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:14313:25"/> 
                  <hi>Paul,</hi> not once to name it, elſe, preſumptuous impiety in the <hi>Papiſts</hi> to match it with <hi>blood</hi> of the ſonne of God.</p>
               <p>Then who is it, was it St. <hi>Peter</hi> whome you bragge to be the founder, nay the foundation of your Church and head of your herarchie? No, that bleſſed Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle renounceth it, for he proclaymeth to all the worlde,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.2.</note> that we are <hi>elect through the ſprinkling of the blood of Ieſus Chriſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.81.</note> heere is no milke: and as we are elect and ſanctified, ſo <hi>redeemed alſo not with things cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible</hi> (therefore not with <hi>milke) but with the precious blood of Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> Behould ye Ieſuits and be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, <hi>Peter</hi> is all in <hi>Blood, blood,</hi> he knowes no milke.</p>
               <p>There remaines but one (for St: <hi>Iames</hi> and St. <hi>Iude</hi> if they name not Chriſts <hi>blood,</hi> I am much more ſure they name no <hi>milke:</hi> was it St. <hi>Iohn the beloued diſciple,</hi> to whome Chriſt <hi>committed her, (as his mother,</hi> but not his Sauiour) no verily, for he is plaine, that not the <hi>milke</hi> of the virgin <hi>Mary,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Iohn. 1.7.</note> but the <hi>blood of Ieſus Chriſt his ſonne clenſeth vs from all our ſinnes:</hi> and that there <hi>are three which beare witnes on earth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Iohn 5.8.</note> 
                  <hi>the ſpirit, and water, and blood:</hi> behold three witneſſes on earth of our ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and redemption, and of them <hi>blood</hi> is one, but <hi>milke</hi> is none, yea <hi>water</hi> is and yet <hi>milke</hi> is not: ſurely if the fathers of the <hi>ſociety</hi> or the <hi>inquiſition</hi> might be Iudges, St. <hi>Iohn</hi> were ſure to be cenſured to remember <hi>water,</hi> and forget <hi>milke.</hi> But ſee how St. <hi>Iohn</hi> and the <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits</hi> differ, they dare match and mixe her <hi>milke</hi> with his <hi>blood,</hi> hee will neither mixe nor match it ſo much as with the <hi>water,</hi> ſhewing that the very <hi>water iſſuing out of his pretious ſide,</hi> was more of worth and value,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:14313:25"/> then all her milke, euen that which fed the fleſh of Chriſt when he was an infant: Nay, the Apoſtle hath not yet done,<note place="margin">Reuel. 1.5.</note> but tels vs that <hi>Chriſt loued vs and waſhed vs</hi> (not in his mothers milke, but) <hi>in his blood:</hi> and that the <hi>Robes of the Saints are made white</hi> (euen white, &amp; yet not in white milke, but) in the red <hi>Blood of the Lambe:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reuel. 7.14<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> See heere, if euer milke had bene apt it had bene here, if euer it had bene ſeaſonable to haue named it, here had bene the place: for what ſhould make white, <hi>milke</hi> or <hi>blood?</hi> and yet the <hi>whiteneſſe</hi> that muſt clothe the Saints; muſt be dyed not in the <hi>milke</hi> of our Lady, but in the <hi>blood</hi> of Ieſus Chriſt, if his beloued and bleſſed Apoſtle <hi>Iohn,</hi> nay if his owne holy word may be belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. If none of all theſe, was it then her ſelfe that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed this potion and made this mixture? no aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly: They ſay we hiſhonor &amp; diſgrace her, yet I dare venture euen my ſoule vpon it, that her hart neuer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to ſuch a thought, as to match &amp; mixe her milk with his blood:<note place="margin">Luke. 1.28.</note> for ſeeing the <hi>Angell</hi> ſaith ſhe was <hi>belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of God,</hi> I am ſure that no creature can be beloued of God, that durſt offer to match the beſt thing in him (if it were his very harts <hi>blood</hi>) with the <hi>blood</hi> of his Son; no his ſoule would hate him, his wrath break out vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him &amp; his vengeance purſue him to deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Farre ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was ſhe from ſo vile a thought:<note place="margin">Luke. 1.47.</note> nay <hi>her ſoule re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyced in him her Sauiour,</hi> ſo farre was ſhe from making her ſelfe in any part a ſauiour of her ſelfe: yea rather, if a Saint in heauen doth heare a blaſphemy on earth, then doutleſſe that bleſſed ſoule of hers, that <hi>magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her ſonne and reioyced in him</hi> as her Sauiour, will neuer
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:14313:26"/> ceaſe to cry and call vpon him, to reuenge ſo high im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety: which is ſo much more haynous, in as much as they make the <hi>mother</hi> the diſhonorer of the <hi>ſonne.</hi> And if her prayers be as powerfull with him as their doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine teacheth, aſſuredly ſhe will not ceaſe to prouoke his iuſtice againſt them, till ſhe haue laid their totte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring kingdome flat on the earth, for erecting vp her as an Idoll againſt her ſonne, and for mixing her milke with his pretious blood.</p>
               <p>Thus then, if neither God the <hi>Father,</hi> nor <hi>Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> nor the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> nor <hi>Moſes,</hi> nor the <hi>Prophets,</hi> nor the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> nor the bleſſed <hi>Virgin</hi> her ſelfe, did any of them preſcribe this potion, nor make this mixture: It followeth, that either the <hi>Diuell</hi> was the deuiſer of it, or elſe that they framed it out of their owne braines and therefore are to be iudged <hi>Mountebankes,</hi> and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall deceiuers, who make ſhew to the worlde, they haue a confection of miraculous vertue, when indeed it is a perfect poyſon to all that take it: for if S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſay true,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Galath. 5.2.</note> that <hi>if we ioyne circumciſion to Chriſt, Chriſt ſhall profit vs nothing:</hi> then without all controuerſie, if we mixe the <hi>milke</hi> of a creature with the <hi>blood</hi> of the mediator, that <hi>blood</hi> of his hath loſt the vertue, and ſhall ptofit vs nothing: And thus the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath ſpunne a faire threed, ſhe will needes haue both the <hi>ſonne</hi> and the <hi>mother</hi> to be hers, in ſuch a maner, as ſhe hath loſt them both, and made them both her enemies, the mother to be her bitter <hi>accuſer,</hi> and the ſonne to be her angry <hi>Iudge.</hi> But thus hath God in Iuſtice blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded her, that whereas for theſe 2: or 300. yeares paſt,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:14313:26"/> ſhe came to this height of blaſphemous deuotion, as to truſt more the piety of the Mother, then the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of the ſonne, &amp; often to appeale from him to her.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">This is ord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nary in many o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>their bookes eſpecially Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nardine de Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to his mariale<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; reuelationes Brigere, and others.</note>Now at laſt by this dealing they haue taken the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect courſe to turne her againſt them alſo, and to make her curſe and abhor them and their ſuperſtition, who dare make her name and her milke to be the diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourers of her ſonne, her Sauiour, and his pretious bloud.</p>
               <p>Thus we haue heard and ſeene the ſtrangeſt peece of phiſicke, and moſt vnequall mixture that yet was euer heard of, The <hi>blood</hi> of God, and <hi>milke</hi> of a woman are mixed to make a cordiall potion, But now what will this potion do, what is the operation of it, hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to the <hi>Mountebankes proclamation,</hi> and he will tell you. Thus he cries,
<q>
                     <l>Vulnera reſtituent turpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vlceribus mendicum,</l>
                     <l>Teſta cui ſaniem reddere ſola poteſt:</l>
                     <l>Vbera reficient Iſmaelem ſitientem</l>
                     <l>Quem Sara non patitur, quem neque nutrit Agar</l>
                     <l>illa mihi ad Peſtem procul &amp; procul expu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>Ista mihi ad lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gas eualitura febres.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>That is,
<q>
                     <l>Theſe <hi>wounds</hi> the ſores do clenſe &amp; cure full wel,</l>
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:14313:27"/>
                     <l>Which none can dreſſe but ſcrape the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with a ſhell</l>
                     <l>Theſe <hi>breſts</hi> the fainting Iſmael wel would cheriſh</l>
                     <l>Who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Sara would not, &amp; Hagar could not noriſh</l>
                     <l>The <hi>firſt</hi> from me expels all peſtilence,</l>
                     <l>The <hi>ſecond</hi> driues all lingring feuers hence.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Now he tells vs what his phiſicke will doe, and that perticularly in both his ſimples, the <hi>blood</hi> &amp; the <hi>milke:</hi> and as for the one of them that is the <hi>blood and wounds</hi> of the mediator, if he had aſcribed much more vnto them, he might haue paſt with praiſe (for vs) for hee cannot ſufficiently extoll the merit &amp; vertue of them, but as for the other, that is the <hi>milke</hi> of a woman, (tho it be the bleſſed virgin) or a confection of both, there he ſheweth himſelfe both impious in making ſuch a mixture, as alſo a vaine deceiuer, proclayming great and ſoueraigne power in that which is nothing worth; for I ſay againe, if it be true that to him that ioyneth <hi>circumſiſion to Chriſt, Chriſt is no Sauiour:</hi> then we dare boldly ſay to him that ioyneth a creatures <hi>milke</hi> in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quallity with Chriſts <hi>blood,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Galath. 5.</note> that <hi>blood</hi> of Chriſt is of no vertue: for <hi>circumſiſion is of the fathers,</hi> nay it was <hi>Gods owne ordination.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Geneſ. 17,</note> But her <hi>milke</hi> is meerely apart (and no eſſentiall part) of her body, which is a creature, and as for the mixture of it with his <hi>blood,</hi> it is an impious deuice of prophane pollititians, not derogating from the dignity, but eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quite abolliſhing the glory of the mediator: then if his paſſion may not be ioyned with circumſiſion, may his blood be mixed with her milke?
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:14313:27"/> But what is it that he proclaymeth <hi>vulnera reſtituent,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Chriſts wounds will reſtore &amp; heale the ſpirituall ſores of a ſinfull Lazar,</hi> we beleeue it wil, they wil do ſo &amp; much more; yet not for his ſake that ſaith ſo, for we knowe that <hi>deuills</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues for a vantage would beare witnes to Chriſt. But for his ſake that ſaid,<note place="margin">Math. 8.29.</note> 
                  <hi>He was wounded for our tranſgreſſions, He was broken for our iniquities,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſay. 53.</note> 
                  <hi>the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſement of our peace was vpon Him, &amp; with His Stripes are we healed:</hi> and for his owne ſake eſpecially, who ſaid it and did it, <hi>I lay downe my life for my Sheep.</hi> Thus he hath ſaid well and truly of the wounds;<note place="margin">Iohn. 10.</note> but the wounds of Chriſt will not ſerue his turne: He therefore addeth.</p>
               <q> Vbera reficient &amp;c.</q>
               <q> The Pappes will quench &amp; refreſh thirſtie ſoules.</q>
               <p>And will they ſo? who taught you that Diuinitie? will a creatures paps quench and ſatiſfie that <hi>ſoule that hungreth and thirſteth after righteouſneſſe?</hi> Say ye chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of iniquitie, haue you not read <hi>Eſay</hi> the Prophet, who tels vs <hi>He</hi> was deſpiſed, <hi>He</hi> was afflicted,<note place="margin">Eſay 53.</note> 
                  <hi>He</hi> was broken, <hi>He</hi> was plagued, and all for vs: <hi>His ſtripes healed vs,</hi> and not a worde of her nor her <hi>Milke,</hi> but al of <hi>him, his ſtripes and his wounds:</hi> what will ye ſay, wanted he <hi>knowledge</hi> of her worthineſſe? or <hi>deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> to her deſerts? Can ye ſay the firſt without blaſphemye to God, or the ſecond without iniurie to the Prophet? could it be he knew not <hi>her</hi> who knew <hi>her ſonne,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Indeed the Papiſts haue taught ſo in former times ſo ſaith their maraile</note> could he foreſee <hi>him</hi> and not <hi>her?</hi> or could any ſuch miſtery be kept fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him who ſpake and wrote, <hi>as he was inſpired by Gods ſpirit?</hi>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:14313:28"/> and to conclude, was it not he that ſaith, <hi>Beholde a virgin ſhall conceiue and bring forth a ſonne, euen Emanu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell Ieſus Chriſt?</hi> ſo that it's plaine as the Prophet knew a <hi>Meſsias</hi> ſhould come and ſhould ſaue his people by dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for them; ſo alſo he foreſaw and knew he ſhould be borne of <hi>a virgin:</hi> If the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the prophet had knowledge of her, dare ye ſay he wanted due deuotion? and yet one of theſe you muſt ſay, and for want of one of theſe you muſt condemne him, who names none but Chriſt, or elſe your ſelues, who dare mixe her <hi>milke with his blood.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But is this all? No,
<q>
                     <l>Illa mihi ad peſtem—</l>
                     <l>Iſta mihi ad febres—</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>One can heale ſpirtuall <hi>peſtilence,</hi> the other ſpirituall <hi>feuers;</hi> ſee what difference there is by their religion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt her <hi>milke</hi> and his <hi>blood:</hi> are not theſe men great and deuout honorers of Chriſt, and his ſuffering that can finde other helpes to heale their ſoules beſides his blood? But if it be thus that both can heale ſo wel, how comes it to paſſe they haue ſo many ſicke ſoules in po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, euen ſicke of all ſpirituall diſeaſes, eſpetially ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by their owne doctrine and daily practiſe, it is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant they can neither want the one nor the other of theſe 2. ſimples: for firſt they ſay they make Chriſts blood euery day, then they haue <hi>blood</hi> at hand conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually: If they ſay that the laytye may not haue that, but onely their Preiſts (who indeede drinke it vp all)
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:14313:28"/> yet then they may take their Ladies <hi>milke</hi> whereof (if themſelues ſay true) they haue ſo much in ſeuerall pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as ſome that liued 100. yeares agoe do write,<note place="margin">Eraſmus and others haue ſpoken more plainely and fully then I d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> that in thoſe dayes, it was more then a woman vpon one childe can giue out, though the childe ſucked none at all: If that that is kept, and ſhewed, and worſhipped in ſo many Citties of <hi>Italy, France, Spaine, Germany,</hi> be not her <hi>milke,</hi> then where is the truth and honeſty of that religion, ſo to deceiue the world? if it be then, why are their ſoules ſo full of ſpirituall diſeaſes? why are they not healed ſeeing this Ieſuit teacheth that <hi>it will heale as well as Chriſts blood?</hi> as wel as Chriſts blood will ſome ſay, why do you them that wrong<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo wicked to ſpeak ſuch blaſphemy. No? then iudge by that which followeth.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Ira vomit fla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mas, fumat<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> libidinis Aetna?</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Suffocare</hi> queo <hi>Sanguine, Lacte</hi> queo,</l>
                  <l>Liuor inexpleta rubigine ſaeuit in artus?</l>
                  <l>Detergere queo <hi>Lacte cruore</hi> queo.</l>
                  <l>Vanus honos me perpetua prurigene te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tat?</l>
                  <l>Exaturare queo <hi>Sanguine, lacte</hi> queo.</l>
               </q>
               <p>That is:
<q>
                     <l>Let <hi>Ire</hi> belch fire and luſt like Etna flame,</l>
                     <l>Chooſe either <hi>milke</hi> or <hi>bloud,</hi> both quench the ſame</l>
                     <l>Let <hi>Enuies</hi> ruſt canker my heart about,</l>
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:14313:29"/>
                     <l>This <hi>milke</hi> that <hi>bloud,</hi> either will fetch it out.</l>
                     <l>Or do <hi>vainglorious</hi> paſſions ſtuffe me ſtill,</l>
                     <l>Either with <hi>milke</hi> or <hi>Bloud</hi> the ſame Ile kill.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Heere iudge and ſpare not (without all partiallity,) whether that I ſaid be not true, that <hi>her milke</hi> wil heale as wel as Chriſts <hi>blood,</hi> and this they affirme, not in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall tearmes but in plaine perticulers: if ſaith he <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> ſwell, if <hi>Luſt</hi> inflame me, <hi>blood</hi> will quench them &amp; ſo wil <hi>milke:</hi> are there two ſtronger <hi>paſſions,</hi> two more conquering <hi>corruptions,</hi> two more raging and raigning ſinnes then Anger and luſt? yet euen theſe two are quenched &amp; conquered by her <hi>milke</hi> as well as <hi>Chriſts blood:</hi> hearken ye Children of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Sinagogue, hearken I ſay what inſtruction your father giues you, heare I pray (but learne it not) a creatures milke will cleanſe your ſoules from ſinne, as wel as your ſauiours blood: O ſpirit of error and blaſphemy, whither wilt thou goe? O Romiſh impiety, when wilt thou make an end? wilt thou not ceaſe till thou haſt puld downe the fire of Gods fury, from heauen vpon thee? <hi>O Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon we would haue healed thee but thou wilt not be healed,</hi> for who can heale him that will needes kill himſelfe? ſo who can heale thee,<note place="margin">Ierem. 51.9.</note> whoſe blaſphemy hath woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and yet benu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>med thy heart, gone ouer thy head, &amp; is <hi>aſcended vp to heauen,</hi> &amp; in the preſence of God crieth vengeance vpon thee; &amp; as for you ſeduced ſoules (my deere cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trymen) you who are deceiued with ſhewes of holyneſſe and deuotion, behold heere a peece of popiſh holyneſſe, and of the doctrine of their deuoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:14313:29"/> that <hi>the ſinnes of the ſoule are cleanſed and taken away aſwell by a creatures milke as by Chriſt his blood!</hi> is this the <hi>catholike</hi> doctrine they brag ſo much of? is this the <hi>ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike</hi> Church that teacheth ſuch diuinity? is this the chaire of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> &amp; the <hi>ſeate</hi> that cannot erre? If it be ſo, then what didſt thou meane thou St. <hi>Iohn</hi> Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt, to teach that it was <hi>Ieſus Chriſt that faithfull wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reuel. 1.5.</note> 
                  <hi>that firſt begotten from the dead, and that Prince of the Kings of the earth</hi> (euen he, and not any creature) <hi>who hath loued vs and waſhed vs from our ſinnes in his blood:</hi> ſure either muſt thou recant this doctrine, els they that boaſt themſelues to be ſucceſſors of thy brother <hi>Peter</hi> may be aſhamed of theirs, who tell vs that <hi>our ſins are waſht away in her milke as well as by his blood:</hi> and you that are the dutiful and deuoted children of that Romiſh ſear, be Iudges euen your ſelues in this caſe, what can be ſaid heereunto: how can it ſtand with ſcripture, or with the tenor of true catholike faith? or how can it any way be defended that a creatures <hi>milke</hi> can quench the fire of ſinne in the ſoule as well as Chriſt his <hi>blood?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Can ye ſay that heere is onely aſcribed to her and her milke, a <hi>deriued</hi> vertue from another, and that the <hi>original</hi> and fundamentall power, is onely and wholy in Chriſt and his blood? if it were ſo it were leſſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill (though Chriſt Ieſus may not, nor will not beſtow the prerogatiues of his Mediatorſhip on any creature) but looke and wade ouer the words againe and again, expound them with any fauour that the wordes may beare, and you ſhall not ſee the leaſt difference.</p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:14313:30"/>
                  <l>Suffocare queo <hi>Sanguine</hi> Lacte queo.</l>
                  <l>Detergere queo <hi>Lacte Cruore</hi> queo.</l>
               </q>
               <p>If <hi>Luſt</hi> burne, <hi>Anger</hi> boyle, <hi>Enuy</hi> fret, <hi>Vaineglory</hi> ſwell I can helpe it with <hi>blood,</hi> ſo can I with <hi>milke:</hi> I can helpe it with <hi>milke,</hi> ſo can I with <hi>bloud:</hi> there can be no grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter equalitie made betwixt any two thinges in the worlde, then here they make betwixt this <hi>Bloud</hi> and <hi>Milke.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Can it be ſaid that the Author is a Poet, and ſaid thus but to make vp the Verſe, which otherwiſe wold not haue falne ſo fitly? ſurely no, for a yong verſifier can ſoone ſhew how the verſes might haue run aſwell as they do, if he had not purpoſely laboured to ſort his verſe to his matter, and not the matter to the verſe:</p>
               <p>For thus he might haue ſaid,
<q>Detergere queo ſanguine Chriſte tuo.</q> with very little alteration.</p>
               <p>And ſo of the reſt: but he as truly endeuoured to magnifie the milke as the bloud, and therefore with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any neceſſitie of the verſe, giues the ſame power, place, &amp; preheminence, in euery reſpect to the milke as to the bloud: but had he bene as ſound and ſincere a Chriſtian as he is a good Poet, he might in as good verſes haue giuen all the honour to Chriſt as he deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth. Therefore (my deere country-men) be no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſeduced by a Religion ſo fraught with Atheiſme, blaſphemy &amp; impyety: doe but looke into the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, Counſels, or Fathers: yea aske the honeſteſt &amp; learnedſt of your owne religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, (or any except Ieſuits
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:14313:30"/> or ſuch other like them, who frame a religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to their owne purpoſes.)</p>
               <p>If this be tollerable Diuinitye, that the <hi>Milke</hi> of the Virgin doth cleanſe mans ſoule from ſinne aſwell as <hi>Chriſt his bloud.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If it be not diuinity but blaſphemy, no Chriſtian doctrine but impiety, and yet ſuffered, yea approued in the Romane Church, both by doctrine and practiſe; then returne to that truth and holy religion, which out of Gods word, and according to the pureſt anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity is eſtabliſhed amongſt vs: &amp; with heart &amp; voice ioyne with vs to imbrace and ſay Amen, to that holy doctrine of bleſſed St. <hi>Iohn,</hi> who ſaith, it is <hi>Ieſus Chriſt that loued vs, and waſhed vs from our ſinnes by his blood, to him be glory for euer and euer, Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This was his religion, this is ours; oh that it were yours alſo! he ſucked this diuinity out of that bleſſed breſt of Gods ſonne, <hi>whereon he leaned:</hi> and if he had ſucked thence this diuinity of the Ieſuits, that the vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin <hi>Mary waſhed vs from our ſinnes by her milke,</hi> ſurely he would neuer haue concealed it from vs, nor haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued her of the <hi>honour,</hi> nor vs of the <hi>comfort</hi> that thereby might accrewe both to her and vs: for he was her <hi>ſonne</hi> by her owne <hi>adoption,</hi> yea her ſonne by the <hi>gift</hi> and nomination of her <hi>ſonne</hi> and ſauiour, yea her ſonne in loue, duty, and all reſpectiueneſſe could he then, or would he in any ſort obſcure her due glory? would he giue too much to her <hi>ſonne,</hi> and too little to <hi>her?</hi> would he giue all that to her <hi>ſonne,</hi> which in parte was <hi>hers?</hi> can this, may this, or dare this be immagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:14313:31"/> by any Ieſuit? If not, then how dare they extend their deuotion beyond <hi>his,</hi> and aſcribe that to her which he neuer did, yea that to <hi>her,</hi> which he appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priates to <hi>Ieſus Chriſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If they thinke that <hi>Peter</hi> had more deuotion then <hi>Iohn,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Pet, 2.24.</note> hearken then what he ſaith: <hi>Ieſus Chriſt his owne ſelfe bare our ſinnes in his body on the tree:</hi> let the words be pondered, Ieſus Chriſt ſaith he bare our ſinnes: true (ſay they) but ſo did the virgin <hi>Mary</hi> alſo, No (ſaith <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>) he <hi>himſelfe, his owne ſelfe</hi> bare them, yea <hi>in his body,</hi> he bare them <hi>in his body:</hi> (ſay they) that is true, but he beares them in his <hi>myſticall body,</hi> in his members, much more therefore in his <hi>mother,</hi> which is more then ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny members of his body; nay ſaith St: <hi>Peter, he bare our ſinnes his owne ſelfe in his body:</hi> but what body? euen that body that was <hi>on the tree:</hi> therefore if St: <hi>Peter</hi> preach true diuinity, then is this doctrine of your Teachers hainous blaſphemy.</p>
               <p>All that may be imagined for their defence at the beſt is this, that all this is but <hi>poeticall,</hi> &amp; hyperbolicall, or proceedes from the paſſion &amp; height of deuotion: but that in truth and earneſt he aſcribes all to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> &amp; to his blood, makes his prayer to him, and puts the confidence of his heart in him alone: but leaſt any man ſhould haue the leaſt ſuſpition of him this way, or thinke ſo good a thought of him, he deales yet more plainely and to preuent all ſuch thoughts and obiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, he makes his prayer both to the mother and the ſonne, without any difference in the world, to the one for her <hi>milke,</hi> to the other for his <hi>blood:</hi> for thus he ſaith.</p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:14313:31"/>
                  <l>Ergo <hi>par ens</hi> et <hi>nate</hi> meis ad vertite votis,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Lac</hi> peto depereo <hi>ſanguinem</hi> vtru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> volo</l>
               </q>
               <p>That is:
<q>
                     <l>Mother and Sonne giue eare to what I craue,</l>
                     <l>I begge this <hi>milke,</hi> that <hi>blood,</hi> &amp; both would haue.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Heere is plaine dealing, it is not the Sonne and his blood that will ſerue his turne, he muſt alſo haue the mother and her milke, is not this good catholike doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine and deuotion? but further is it not ſtrange to ſee how he marſhalls them in the order of his iudgement and affection? he prayeth to the mother and the ſonne; but firſt to the <hi>mother,</hi> hee will haue both milke and blood, but firſt <hi>milke:</hi> thus <hi>Mary</hi> hath the precedence of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and her milke of his blood: But you will ſay it is not that he ſo eſteemes them in his iudgement, but onely for the neceſſitie of the verſe: the anſwere is that a grammer ſcholler, can ſoone ſhewe how the verſe is as good, and giue <hi>Chriſt</hi> his precedence, as it is doing him this wrong:
<q>Ergo Nate parenſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> meis aduertite votis,</q>
               </p>
               <p>But he ſtil keeping Chriſt in <hi>wardſhip</hi> and vnder age, held it not fit that he ſhould haue the place before his mother onely, and therefore without all neceſſitie e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen wittingly and wilfully, he puts Chriſt in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond place. But now let vs haſten to an end of this (if it be not endleſſe and bottomeleſſe) impiety.</p>
               <p>Vpon theſe fearefull premiſes thus he proceedes,
<q>
                     <pb n="60" facs="tcp:14313:32"/>
                     <l>Paruule maternis medius qui ludis in vlnis</l>
                     <l>et tua iam comples vbera, iam vacuas:</l>
                     <l>Quid me reſpectas obliqua tue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tibus hirquis</l>
                     <l>Roboris in Coelum nil habet inuidia.</l>
                     <l>Saepe quidem dixti, noxis offenſus iniquis,</l>
                     <l>Tune meas <hi>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mas,</hi> Improbe, tune meas?</l>
                     <l>Nolo tuas ó nolo tuas puer auree <hi>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mas:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Non ſum tam duri, ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> grauis oris homo:</l>
                     <l>ſed ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                        <hi>lateris</hi> pluat vnica &amp; vnica ſtilla:</l>
                     <l>Et ſaltem a dextrae vulnere gutta pluat.</l>
                     <l>Si nihil è dextrâ visimpluere, implue <hi>laeuâ:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Si nihil é laeuâ, de pede ſanguis eat.</l>
                     <l>Si tibi non placeo vulnus mihi vulnera da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to</l>
                     <l>Mercedem danto vulnera, ſi placeo.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>In Engliſh thus,
<q>
                     <l>Youngling that in thy mothers armes art playing,</l>
                     <l>Sucking her breſt ſomtimes &amp; ſomtimes ſtaying,</l>
                     <l>Why doſt thou view me with that look of ſcorne</l>
                     <l>Its forceles enuie that gainſt thee is borne.</l>
                     <l>Oft haſt thou ſaid, being angry at my ſinne,</l>
                     <l>Dareſt thou deſire the <hi>teats</hi> my foode lies in?</l>
                     <pb n="61" facs="tcp:14313:32"/>
                     <l>I will not, oh I dare not (noble childe)</l>
                     <l>Dutie from me is not ſo far exilde:</l>
                     <l>But one, euen one poore drop I doe implore,</l>
                     <l>from thy right <hi>hand</hi> or <hi>ſide</hi> I aske no more.</l>
                     <l>If neither: from thy <hi>left hand</hi> let one fall,</l>
                     <l>nay from thy foote rather then none at all.</l>
                     <l>doſt thou diſlike me? let thy wounds me wound,</l>
                     <l>But pay my due, if I in grace be found.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Now from blaſphemy he proceedes to plain Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſme, not fearing to expoſe the greateſt myſteries of Chriſtian faith, and euen our bleſſed Sauiour himſelf, to the ridiculous &amp; ſcornefull contempt of prophane men: Speaking vnto Chriſt, God coaequall with the father, and whoſe very humanity raigneth now in glory at Gods right hand, as to a ſeely infant in his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers armes: and to him whoſe very humanity is fedde with the gloryous preſence and contemplation of the deity, as to a poore <hi>childe ſucking</hi> his mothers breſts: ſuch conceits are common, and ſuch words and wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings rife with them, of our bleſſed Sauiour, who ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſpeake of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> but with the title of <hi>Queene of heauen, Lady of Angels,</hi> the <hi>gate of Paradice,</hi> the <hi>fountaine of mercy,</hi> or ſome ſuch other titles, fitting none but him that is God, or at the leaſt ſhe is alwaies a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunding Mother, and he an infant gouerned and an obedient childe: But let vs conſider his words a little better. <hi>Paruule &amp;c. youngling</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>thou pretty babe, that playeſt in thy mothers armes, and ſometimes ſuckes
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:14313:33"/> her breſtes till they be emptie, and againe ſtayeſt till they be full. &amp;c.</hi> Is this good and ſound Diuinity, that Chriſt our Redeemer is now this preſent yeare, at <hi>Halla</hi> in <hi>Brabant,</hi> an <hi>Infant</hi> playing in <hi>his Mothers armes, &amp; ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king her breſts?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If it be ſo, then ſure St. <hi>Paul</hi> was much to blame to teach vs, that euen <hi>the man Ieſus Chriſt, after he had offred one ſacrifice for ſinnes, ſitteth for euer</hi> (not in his mothers armes, but) <hi>at his Fathers right hand:</hi> and what doing? not playing in her armes, nor ſucking her breſts, but there <hi>he euer liueth to make interceſsion for vs.</hi> Interceſſion! to whome? not to <hi>her</hi> in whoſe armes they will make him play, but <hi>to him, at whoſe right hand he ſitteth for euermore.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And much more to blame St <hi>Peter,</hi> who (not fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeing, it ſeemes what doctrine his pretended ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor would teach after him) teacheth vs that <hi>Ieſus Chriſt is at Gods right hand, gone into heauen, to whome Angelles, powers &amp; might are ſubiect.</hi> Are Angels, powers &amp; might ſubiect to him? &amp; muſt he be ſubiect to a mortall &amp; hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane creature? Nay, is he now an <hi>Infant,</hi> playing in his mothers armes, and hanging on her breſts? is not this good Catholik Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iſh <hi>doctrine?</hi> &amp; is not this good pure Romiſh <hi>deuotion,</hi> to pray to him who is God of glory, &amp; whoſe manhood is now at Gods right hand, Angels and powers ſubiect to him, in ſuch wordes as theſe: <hi>Thou pritty Childe that playeſt in thy mothers armes, &amp; han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt at her breſts?</hi> Is this a ſaluation fit for the Sonne of God, who is the <hi>Sonne conſecrated for euer?</hi> the <hi>heire of all thinges,</hi> the <hi>brightnes of Gods glory, and the ingrauen
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:14313:33"/> forme of his perſon?</hi> or is this a Chriſtian like deſcription of him, who <hi>hauing by himſelfe purged our ſinnes, fitteth at the right hand of the maiestie in the higheſt places?</hi> But this is naturall to Popiſh religion, to diſgrace the <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator</hi> they care not how, ſo that they may aduaunce ſome creatures, and magnifie their owne deuiſes: but though they neuer ſo much abuſe moſt of Gods <hi>ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances,</hi> and nullifie the very Offices of the Mediator, Yet me thinks they ſhould be a little feareful how they touch the perſon it ſelfe of the mediator and ſonne of God, and ſhould ſhrinke and ſhame to expoſe the perſon of Ieſus Chriſt, to the baſe conceit of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly: for what can the carnall man, much more the <hi>Atheiſt,</hi> the <hi>Turke,</hi> and the <hi>Iewe</hi> imagine of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> when he that is his pretended Vicar ſuffers his followers to ſpeake and write of him, and pray to him, as a <hi>playing childe,</hi> and <hi>ſucking infant,</hi> and to deſcribe him in his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiours as a very childe, greeuing and crying that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſhould <hi>touch his mothers paps</hi> but onely himſelfe? alas what will this religion of Rome do at laſt? the <hi>word</hi> of God and <hi>Sacraments</hi> and other his holy <hi>ordinances</hi> they haue prophaned, the <hi>officer</hi> of the Mediator haue they nullified, and yet not content: heere they labour to make rediculous to all irreligious men, the very <hi>perſon</hi> of Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe: could this be done by any but them that are the Children of that mother of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, <hi>that ſits vpon the beaſt full of names of blaſphemy?</hi> ariſe O Lord, maintaine thine owne cauſe, deliuer thy holy name from that pollution, and thy religion from that contempt which they bring vpon it. To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude:
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:14313:34"/> it may not be amiſſe heere to obſerue the oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition betwixt God in his holy ſcripture, and the Pope in this his religion.</p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <note place="margin">1. Cor. 5.16.</note>
                           <hi>The Scrpture ſaith, Chriſte</hi> Ieſus is no more to be knowne after the fleſh.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Popeay ſaith,</hi> Chriſt is yet to be knowne and worſhipped as a childe.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <note place="margin">Heb. 1.3.</note>
                           <hi>The Scripture ſaith, Chriſt</hi> bears vp all thinges by his mighty worde.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Popery ſaith,</hi> chriſt is now borne in his mothers armes.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <note place="margin">Heb. 9.</note>
                           <hi>The Scripture ſaith, Chriſt</hi> ſitteth for euer at the right hand of God.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Popery ſaith,</hi> Chriſt is playing in his mothers armes.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <note place="margin">Pſal. 110.</note>
                           <hi>The Scripture ſaith, Chriſt</hi> tarieth at his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers right hand, till his enemyes bee made his footſtoole.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Popery ſoith,</hi> Hee is in heauen, till it pleaſe the Pope to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low a picture at Hal or Sichem.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <note place="margin">1. Tim. 3.16.</note>
                           <hi>The Scripture ſaith,</hi> Without Controuerſye great is the myſtery of godlyneſſe that Ieſus Chriſt is receiued vp into glory.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Popery ſaith,</hi> Without controuerſie, that it is no ſuch myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, for Chriſt is ſtill in his mothers armes.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> 
                           <note place="margin">Luke. 24.</note>
                           <pb n="65" facs="tcp:14313:34"/>
                           <hi>The Scripture ſaith,</hi> Chriſt muſt ſuffer and ſo enter into his glory.</cell>
                        <cell> 
                           <hi>Popery ſaith,</hi> Chriſt after all his ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, muſt againe be ſubiect to the infirmy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of an infant.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>Out of all this followeth a concluſion of good vſe: It hath bene often obiected to the Romiſh Church, that they haue not <hi>true Chriſt</hi> left amongſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but an Idoll of their owne rearing, erected in their owne carnall fancies: now that this is no ſlaunder, no cauill, no hybolicall nor figuratiue ſpeech, nor an accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on forced vpon them againſt their wills, is apparant by their owne doctrine and practiſe in this place: for the <hi>Chriſt</hi> of God and of his Church, is God equall to the father, and can do all things himſelfe: the Chriſt of the Romiſh church is a childe inferiour to his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and may deny her nothing. The <hi>true Chriſt,</hi> being man <hi>grew in ſtature and wiſedome,</hi> and being growne a man, ſo liued and dyed, roſe againe and was glorified, and neuer decreaſed: but <hi>theirs</hi> is now become a childe againe and a playing infant: the true <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſitteth at the right hand of God his father, theirs is borne in the armes of <hi>Mary</hi> his mother.</p>
               <p>Hence the concluſion is euident, that therefore the Romiſh Chriſt is not the true chriſt of God and of the true chriſtian church. This concluſion I demonſtrate thus: the title of theſe verſes is this, <hi>To our Lady of Hall, and the Childe Ieſus:</hi> this childe they ſpeake of is either Ieſus Chriſt indeed or it is not: if not, then they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:14313:35"/> them ſelues lyers and impoſtors: if it be, then my concluſion ſtands good: for this Ieſus, in all the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named reſpects, and many more, differeth from the true Ieſus and ſauiour of Chriſtian men: let them take whether they will, the better is to bad. But now let vs ſee what is that he ſaith to this childe Ieſus.</p>
               <q>Quid me reſpectas &amp;c.</q>
               <p>Why (ſaith he) doeſt thou frowne on me (thou prety childe) <hi>art thou angry with me for deſiring thy milke? doeſt thou chide me that I dare preſume to aske the milke of thy mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers teates?</hi> this is all the cauſe he layeth of Chriſt his anger, what ſhold a man ſay to this? what would a Iew ſay, what will an Atheiſt thinke of it? ſurely they will deride and laugh at that religion that allowes it, if our Chriſt be ſuch a one as is angry at ſuch a cauſe: But ſay I pray thee thou Romiſh Ieſuit, (thou wanteſt neither wit nor learning to giue anſwer) ſpeakeſt thou in ieſt or earneſt? If in <hi>Ieſt,</hi> then, knoweſt thou with whome thou ieſteſt? conſidereſt thou that it is <hi>Ieſus of Nazareth,</hi> the great one of <hi>God,</hi> he <hi>of whoſe kingdome there ſhall be no end,</hi> he that is <hi>the brightnes of Gods glory and the ingrauen forme of his perſon,</hi> he at whoſe remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance the diuels tremble, &amp; to whome <hi>all knees bowe in</hi> heauen, earth, and hell' and dareſt thou exerciſe thy wit, and whet thy ſtile, and practiſe thy poetical vaine vpon him? and vnto him that now hauing conquered ſinne, death, and hell? <hi>ſitteth now at the right hand of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty, in the higheſt places?</hi> dareſt thou preſent ſuch a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition as this? <hi>O pretty childe doe not enuy me that I ſhould touch thy mothers paps, with which I perceiue thou wilt ſuffer
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:14313:35"/> none to play but thy ſelfe: oh be not angry that I long for that which is thine, namely, for the milke of thy mothers teats?</hi> didſt thou euer finde in ſcriptures or ſound antiquity, that any holy man did euer conceiue of him, or ſpeake to him on this faſhion? no for its rather aſporting ſpeech fit to be ſpoken to a playing <hi>childe,</hi> then a ſalutation fit to be tendered to the ſonne of God &amp; Sauiour of the world:</p>
               <p>But if thou ſay thou ſpeakſt in <hi>earneſt</hi> according to the truth of religion, and ſoundneſſe of diuinity, then tel me I pray thee in earneſt, is this any part of chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an faith, or is it catholike diuinity, that <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> is offended with that man that ſhall deſire to touch the Virgin <hi>Maries papps,</hi> or to taſte of her milke (not in this regard that its a thing not poſſible, and therefore in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede not to be wiſhed by a Chriſtian, but) becauſe they be peculiarly &amp; propperly his paps &amp; his milke, ſtill as they were when he was an infant? If this be Romiſh diuinity, alas for the ſheep that are fed in ſuch paſtures, and filld with ſuch doctrine: for this is funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tally both falſe &amp; impious, <hi>falſe,</hi> for if it be true that the holy ſcriptures teach,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 5.</note> that <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> is now no more to be <hi>knowne</hi> nor conceyued of <hi>according to the fleſh,</hi> that is as a meere and mortall man, but as a <hi>glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied</hi> man, a ſpirituall conquerour of his enemies, and a ſpirituall head of his Church. If this I ſay be true, that he is no longer to be knowne as a man, as he was vpon earth, then it is falſe that he is ſtill to be concey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of and ſpoken vnto as a playing childe: Beſides it is impious and irreligious, and a ſtep to Atheiſme to
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:14313:36"/> imagine that Chriſt our God and Sauiour, is offended for ſuch an imaginary toy as this is, to touch his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers <hi>paps,</hi> or to deſire her <hi>milke:</hi> and what enemies of our religion would not loudly laugh at this our <hi>Chriſt</hi> whome we ſo magnifie, that we make him the reſt of our ſoules, to be ſuch a one as he is heere deſcribed? namely one that chides him that dare touch his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers paps, for ſo ſaith the verſe:
<q>Tune meas Mammas improbe tune meas?</q>
               </p>
               <p>That is:
<q>Dareſt thou deſire the teates, my food lyes in?</q> Alas how ſhall the mouthes of <hi>Turkes</hi> and <hi>Iewes</hi> be ſtopped from blaſpheming, and ſaying: Is this your Chriſt? is this the glory of chriſtianitie? is this he whome you make a God? are theſe the <hi>ſins</hi> he is offended withall? Surely no wayes can ſuch and fowler blaſphemyes be preuented, but that the Chriſtian world publikely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce, condemne, and curſe, this damned doctrine, as being the priuate and impious blaſphemye of the Machiuillian Ieſuits, but not the Catholike doctrine of chriſtianity: For we cannot deny but there is a <hi>gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of vipers,</hi> bred of the corruption and putrifacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of an olde and ſinfull world; calling themſelues <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites,</hi> or Prieſts of the ſocietie of Ieſus: who as they come neareſt to God in their mouthes; ſo are they in their hearts (if their courſes can diſcouer them) the furtheſt from him. With theſe fellowes it may be it is a doctrine or a peece of deuotion, that it's a great ſin for a man to deſire fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ieſus ſome of his <hi>mothers milke:</hi>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:14313:36"/> but if they be asked who made this a ſin, they muſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, themſelues: if what law? euen their owne fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies: But as for the catholike &amp; chriſtian Church, <hi>ſhe</hi> dooth renounce it.</p>
               <p>But to proceede, is it not ſtrange that a witty and learned Ieſuit, ſhould frame ſuch a ſpeech as this vnto <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> for thus to begin, <hi>Oh bleſſed Childe why art thou angry at me, and offended with me? oft haſt thou ſaid to me being angry at my ſinnes, &amp;c.</hi> would put a man in hope that ſome great matter followed: for vpon ſo good a beginning, would not a man preſume that ſome good confeſſion of ſinnes ſhould follow? as this, I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe o Lord I haue ſinned in ignorance, in ſelfe-loue, in ſecurity, in hardneſſe of heart, in incontinency, in mallice, in hatred, in couetouſnes, in omiſſion of my duties, in commiſſion of euill &amp;c. for theſe O Lord, and for any of theſe, thou mighteſt ſay vnto me, thou miſerable wretch, how dareſt thou thus pollute my name, and as farre as in thee lyeth, <hi>crucifie me againe,</hi> by theſe thy ſins? how dareſt thou <hi>duſt and aſhes,</hi> thus vilifie my eternall law, the curſe whereof thou haſt heereby incurred? how dareſt thou beare my name, or looke me in the face, whome thou haſt thus prouoked? oh that our eares might haue heard a Ieſuit ſaying thus, and ſurely in reaſon a man would haue expected ſome ſuch co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluſion from ſuch a beginning. But why ſhould we looke for either reaſon or religion from a Ieſuite?<note place="margin">
                     <p>See <hi>Watſon</hi> the Preiſt hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> iudgement the Ieſuit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten in his quidlibets.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Coſterus</hi> in <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>chiridio: cap calibatu ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>d:</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>cerdos ſi for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catur aut d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>i co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ucubinam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>eat tamet ſi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>us ſacrilig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>tringet raeuius tamen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ccat ſi malit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>enirum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> hat.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>his is alſo by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>efended both <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>retſer</hi> the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>it in his <hi>hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>oria ord. Ieſ.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d by <hi>Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>us armandus</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e Ieſuit, in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s Epiſtles to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hamier: vid. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Ieſuiticas. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r the points <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſwearing &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>oly daies, ſee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ollet in his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſtructioſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r dotum: &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>zorius in his <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſtitutiones orales Sixtus</hi> fiue made that a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>int at King <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>helops</hi> requeſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pence expreſly) of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>is inuaſion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>f <hi>England.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>88.</p>
                  </note> (if that be true which their brother <hi>Watſon</hi> the Prieſt hath written of them.) To haue ſuppoſed Chriſt to be angry with him for breaking the morrall lawe had
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:14313:37"/> bene good diuinity, and no poeticall immagination, but theſe holy fathers haue no ſuch faults: nay ſee how innocent Lambes the Ieſuits be, that when chriſt is moſt angry with a <hi>Ieſuit,</hi> and rebukes him for ſinne, he hath none to lay to his charge, nor finde any wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he is guilty, but a little holy <hi>preſumption,</hi> or rather height of ardent <hi>deuotion,</hi> that he dare touch the <hi>papps,</hi> and beg the <hi>milke</hi> of the virgin <hi>Mary:</hi> o fearefull pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, o carnall ſelfe-loue, o helliſh pride, and well beſeeming the Ieſuiticall broode! is not this the <hi>generation that praiſeth it ſelfe,</hi> and (as Salomon ſaith) <hi>is good in his owne eies?</hi> But ſay in earneſt, is this all the fault that thou thinkeſt chriſt can finde with thee? then belike there is either no breaches at all of the morrall law, amongſt Ieſuits, or els the breaches of Gods lawe, are leſſe ſinnes amongſt them, then are the brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of their owne deuiſes, and well may it be ſo: for he was a Ieſuit who taught that <hi>a Prieſt ſinneth leſſe if he keepe a whore, or lye with another mans wife, then if he mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry a wife of his owne,</hi> I ſay he was a <hi>Ieſuit</hi> that wrote it, and he was a <hi>Ieſuit</hi> that defended it.</p>
               <p>Againe, they teach that its a leſſe ſinne to <hi>ſweare</hi> in common talke by the holy name of God, then it is to <hi>eat an egge</hi> in lent: for the latter ſay they is a <hi>mortall</hi> ſin, the firſt is but a <hi>veniall.</hi> Againe, that he ſins no more that workes vpon the holy <hi>Saboth</hi> day then hee that workes vpon the feaſt day of St. <hi>Didace</hi> the Spaniard whome <hi>Sixtus</hi> made a Saint, not yet 20. yeares agoe: they whoſe doctrines theſe &amp; ſuch others be, no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell tho they holde that the breach of a duty of their
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:14313:37"/> owne deuiſing, is a greater ſinne then the breach of the morall lawe: for ſo muſt he holde that wrote this, or els that chriſt can finde no greater fault in him, but that he durſt beg his mothers milke: or els that Chriſt would paſſe by al other faults in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of that, let him chuſe which of the three dooth pleaſe him beſt, for one he muſt needes take, or elſe confeſſe that all this while he is but in ieſt.</p>
               <p>I would leaue this point, but that my loue to you (my deere country-men, the papiſts of England) pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke me to one word more, to you and for your ſakes.</p>
               <p>Conſider I pray you what theſe men are, who be the Fathers and founders, at leaſt the guiders and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours of your faith: A generation that knowes no euill by it ſelfe, but this that I dare ſtand to is no euill at all, but of their owne making, a generation againſt whome Chriſt hath nothing but this ridiculous alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation which you haue heard of: which if it be true, as they are a ſocietie of all the world to be <hi>honoured,</hi> ſo being falſe, they are a broode of hypocrites, of all the worlde to be <hi>deteſted:</hi> Then ſee how, you are dayly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witched by their inchauntments, and caried vp and downe as they pleaſe to lead you: but conſider I pray you what will not thoſe men ſay of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to you in priuate, which ſpeake thus inſolently of themſelues in publike? what meruailous, miraculous, and incredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble things wil not theſe fellowes buz into the eares of their nouices (whome they endeauour to binde pren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes to their <hi>Belzebub?</hi>) who dare offer to publiſh to the eyes and cenſure of all the world, that Chriſt lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth nothing to their charge vnleſſe it be an extremity
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:14313:38"/> of deuotion, to his bleſſed mother: O beloued coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trymen, be not ſeduced by ſuch <hi>impoſtors!</hi> let not ſuch <hi>vipers</hi> eat out your hearts; but diſcouer the hypocrites and ſend them home vnmasked to hell where they were hatched, for they that dare thus dally with our Sauiour, no maruaile tho they be ſo bold with your ſoules and your conſciences, your children, and your eſtates and all that belongs you.</p>
               <p>Now to goe forward, he hath tolde vs the great quarrell that Chriſt hath to him, and the hideous fault for which he chides him, that he offers to touch his <hi>mothers teates,</hi> and will needes haue ſome of her <hi>milke:</hi> but now let vs ſee what he anſwers &amp; how he defends himſelfe.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Nolo tuas ô nolo tuas puer auree ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mas.</l>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <l>I will not, oh I dare not, golden childe:</l>
                  <l>Duty from me is not ſo farre exilde:</l>
                  <l>But one, euen one poore drop I doe implore,</l>
                  <l>From thy right hand or ſide, I aske no more.</l>
               </q>
               <p>To a ſtrange accuſation heere is a more ſtrange anſwer: for now the tide of his blaſphemy is almoſt at the higheſt: the quarrell he ſuppoſed Chriſt to haue againſt him, was that he durſt preſume to touch his <hi>mothers paps,</hi> or deſire to taſte of her <hi>milke:</hi> a fearefull ſinne doutleſſe, yet neither forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in the Lawe nor the Goſpel, but a ſinne of the Popes making. But what is his anſwer hereunto? he
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:14313:38"/> plainely pleads <hi>not guilty,</hi> alleadging for himſelfe, that he is not ſo bold, ſo rude, ſo preſumptuous, as to dare to entertaine any ſuch thought, or attempt any ſuch thing, as to touch her ſacred <hi>paps,</hi> or to drinke of that glorious <hi>milke:</hi> no his ambitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reacheth not ſo high, he onely prayeth to haue part of his <hi>wounds</hi> and <hi>blood,</hi> that he deſireth as being a thing of an inferiour nature and not comparable to the other.</p>
               <p>O miſerable times of ours, that we ſhould liue to ſee that any mans heart ſhould conceiue, any mans tonge vtter, eſpecially any mans penne ſhould publiſh ſuch horrible blaſphemy againſt the blood and perſon of our Sauiour! what, muſt the Virgin Mary be firſt compared, afterward equalled, &amp; is not that inough vnles now ſhe be preferred before, and aduanced a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue Chriſt? is his blood inferiour to her milke? and is it leſſe preſumptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be bold with Chriſt then her? whither will Romiſh religion goe at the laſt, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie comes to this?</p>
               <p>But to come to a more perticular conſideration of the wordes: the anſwer that here the Ieſuits makes, containes apparantly both abſurditie and impietie, &amp; both in the higheſt degree: The abſurditie appeares in the euident <hi>contradiction</hi> of himſelfe; for now, as tho he had either forgotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or cared not what he ſaid afore, He denyeth that which afore he ſpake almoſt in euery verſe: dare you not now touch her <hi>paps,</hi> nor taſte her <hi>milke?</hi> then who was it that afore ſaid, <hi>I am doutfull whether to take paps or ſide, milke or blood: If I looke at the paps, I long for milke: if at the wounds, I would haue blood:
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:14313:39"/> ſeeing therefore both are ſo good, I will haue both: I will catch the milke with my right hand, the blood with my left.</hi> Didſt thou this euen now, &amp; now ſaiſt thou <hi>dare not touch it?</hi> Nay, was it not thou that ſaidſt <hi>I will mingle the milke of the mother with the blood of the Sonne,</hi> and ſo make a ſoueraigne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pound to heale my ſoule, &amp; now dareſt thou not <hi>touch the milke nor paps?</hi> was it not thy mouth that ſaid, <hi>if Anger, Luſt, or any ſinne vexe my ſoule, blood will help it, and ſo will milke: therefore mother and Sonne heare my requeſt, I muſt haue milke, I will haue blood, I will haue both?</hi> and doſt thou now ſay, oh I will haue <hi>blood</hi> indeede, but I dare not deſire <hi>milke?</hi> was it then deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to <hi>take</hi> it, and <hi>taſte</hi> it, and <hi>drinke</hi> it, and <hi>mingle</hi> it with Chriſts blood, and apply it to the ſoule, and is it now preſumption to deſire it? can one mouth ſend out ſuch groſſe <hi>contradictions?</hi> but let it paſſe, for no abſurdity nor contradiction can be ſo vile as ſhould euer haue moued me to haue ſet pen to paper at this time, (for they are ſufficiently diſcouered already in theſe and other points,) but when diſhonour and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy is offered to the blood &amp; perſon of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> how can a chriſtian hold his peace? for if that be true which the learned father ſaith,<note place="margin">Hieronim.</note> that <hi>in accuſation of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie he would haue no man patient,</hi> wheras <hi>hereſie</hi> is but the ſhame and hurt of the man that holdes it? then ſure in the caſe of <hi>blaſphemy</hi> and impiety, touching the very crowne, and ſtriking at the head of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> our lord and redeemer, who can be patient, who can but ſpeak? neither thinke that heerein I chalenge ought to my ſelfe aboue my bretheren, but knowe contrariwiſe, that though I only write, who firſt, or with the firſt that
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:14313:39"/> diſcouered it, yet ſpeake I, and write I in the perſon of many millions more, who all with one heart and voice deteſt this Romiſh impiety.</p>
               <p>The <hi>impiety</hi> that bewrayes it ſelfe in this anſwere is ſuch as goeth beyond all we yet heard, and wherein it ſeemes the blaſphemer thought to exceed himſelfe. That we may the better diſcouer it marke the curre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of his ſpeech: <hi>O Chriſt</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>oft haſt thou being prouoked with my ſinne, rebuked me and ſaid: dareſt thou ſinfull wretch preſume to touch my teates or medle with the milk that feedes me?</hi> he anſwereth, <hi>oh no bleſſed childe I dare not, nor I will not ſo farre preſume, I neuer was ſo rude, nor ſo vnci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil, as to imagine that I might touch thoſe precious papps, or taſte the bleſſed milke of thy mother: I onely beg a little of thine owne blood, from thy ſide, thy hand or foote: that ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent me:</hi> what is this we heare? you are content to haue <hi>Chriſts blood,</hi> but as for the virgin <hi>Maries milke</hi> thou da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt not deſire it: what, is her milk more pretious, more dainty, more ſacred then the <hi>blood</hi> of the mediator? Yee heauens be aſtonied at this, and all yee creatures of God (in your kindes) renounce and deteſt this hay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous blaſphemy. And you (my poore countrymen) that are the devoted children of that church, beholde heere a peece of popiſh diuinity and deuotion, <hi>a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures milke is of more eſteeme then Chriſt his blood: a chriſtian by the power of his ordinary ſauing faith, may be partaker of the benefits of Chriſts blood, but not of the bleſſed milke of our Lady. The blood he may boldly challenge, the milke he ſcarce may name: in the blood he may diue and waſh his ſoule, the milke he may not preſume to touch:</hi> oh new diuinity, for
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:14313:40"/> merly it ſeemed ſtrange that her <hi>milke</hi> was but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to his <hi>blood,</hi> but when after it was made equall to it, and mingled with it, and held as fit to heale the ſoule as it that ſeemed incredible, till we ſawe it: then what is this that now we heare, that her milke is not onely <hi>comparable</hi> nay <hi>equall</hi> but euen <hi>more pretious,</hi> more ſacred, more excellent then the blood of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt:</hi> oh miſerable religion of <hi>popery,</hi> whether wilt thou draw thy deceiued children in the end? what will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of thee and thy followers? If the diuels confeſſed that <hi>Ieſus of Nazareth was the Chriſt of God,</hi> that is the onely Sauiour of the world, and the onely a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nointed of God, to be the mediator, and yet for all this are <hi>diuelt</hi> ſtill and no better: then what are they and what a reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is that, which makes his <hi>blood</hi> not ſo good, ſo ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, ſo ſoueraigne, ſo pretious as her <hi>milke,</hi> and ſo by conſequent will neither let him be the onely nor the principall Sauiour. Now the ſame glorious God and Sauiour <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> whoſe merrits are debaced, whoſe perſon diſhonored, and whoſe blood little bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then troden vnder foote, either conuert in mercy, or in iuſtice confound all that ſhall conſent, defend or giue countenance to ſo fearefull a blaſphemy: and the ſame God giue you grace poore ſeduced Engliſhmen to relinquiſh that religion, which is the mother of ſuch monſters as vpon this <hi>theater of the Ieſuits,</hi> are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented vnto you: and eſpetially to deteſt that Ieſuiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical ſect, whoſe honor it is to diſhonour Ieſus Chriſt, and who bring vpon <hi>the great theater of their honour,</hi> the <hi>blood</hi> of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> ſo diſhonoured, as it yet neuer was by
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:14313:40"/> any ſect or profeſſion, Turke or Iewe, Atheiſt, or here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike, deuill or man, ſince the world began.</p>
               <p>But let vs ſee what remaineth.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sepae mihi Babilon patera propinat et auro</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ingeminatque meis auribus, euge, bibe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>non faciam, vel ſi Coelum miſce bitur Orco</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Non faciam, meretrix impia, non faciam</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>O ſitio tamen, o vocem ſitis intercludit:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nate</hi> cruore <hi>ſitem co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prime,</hi> lacte <hi>pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <l>Oft times doth <hi>Babilon</hi> in golde me proffer,</l>
                  <l>Delicious drinke, and wooes me to her offer:</l>
                  <l>No, no, thogh heauen &amp; hel ſhould meet, Ile none</l>
                  <l>Ile none, vngratious ſtrumpet hence be gone:</l>
                  <l>But ah I thirſt, a drought my breaſt doth ſmother</l>
                  <l>Quench me with <hi>blood</hi> ſweete ſonne, with <hi>milke</hi> good mother.</l> 
               </q>
               <p>After the diſcourſe imagined (as we heard before) to be betwixt <hi>Chriſt</hi> and him, contayning <hi>Chriſts</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation and his defence touching the high pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption of being as bolde with his mothers <hi>milke</hi> as his <hi>blood:</hi> now ſodainely he turnes himſelfe from <hi>Chriſt</hi> to <hi>Babylon</hi> and ſuppoſeth that <hi>Babylon</hi> that ſpirituall ſtrumpet allures him to her vnlawfull luſts
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:14313:41"/> and vilde idolatries, and that her temptations haue bene both frequent and forcible. And ſurely heerein we eaſily beleeue him: for what is ſpirituall <hi>Babylon</hi> but the Kingdome of ſinne and Sathan, of impiety, I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry, blaſphemy, ſuperſtition, prophanes: and where is that as in <hi>Popery,</hi> and where to be found ſo fully as in the bowels of the Popiſh ſtate, whome they well know all the world either cleerely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnes, or at leaſt iuſtly ſuſpects to be that ſpirituall <hi>Babylon</hi> ſo fearefully accurſed and condemned in the Reuelation. For what Citty is ſo notoriouſly knowne to ſtand vpon the notable and famous hills as <hi>Rome</hi> is? what Citty in all the world did <hi>raigne ouer all the Kings of the earth,</hi> then when St. Iohn wrote, but onely Rome? and the text ſaith (as plainely as can be) that the <hi>woman, the great whore, great Babylon the mother of fornications, is that great Cittie that raigneth ouer the kings of the earth:</hi> &amp; laſtly there is no place, perſon, ſtate, nor power, in the world, in whome the number of 666 ſo fully concurreth, in ſo many languages, in ſo many reſpects, ſo directly; and with ſo little ſtrayning as in the Popes.</p>
               <p>I will ſpecifie but fewe for many, the Pope or none but the Pope chalendgeth to be the Prince of al the clergy in the world, and therefore in theſe latter yeares hath calld himſelfe vniuerſall Biſhop, and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor of Paſtors: Now it falls out that this his pride doth proclaime his ſhame to all the world, for the number of the beaſt is in this name, without adding, altering, or any ſtrayning, as he ſhall finde that will reckon.</p>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:14313:41"/>
               <p>DVX. CLerI</p>
               <p>500. 5. 10. 100. 50. 1. Totall: 669.</p>
               <p>Againe, the Pope glorieth in this title and honour, that he is <hi>Gods generall Vicar on earth:</hi> this is the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all his pretended power and vſurpation: this he and his imps fight for as for their liues.</p>
               <p>This his ſeduced creatures, Engliſh Prieſts and Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits, doe in England dye for (excepting ſome that dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for horrible treaſons) and no maruel, for they know they looſe all if they looſe this, and yet the Pope can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not holde it, but withall he muſt haue the number of <hi>the beaſt</hi> ingrauen in his forehead, ſo as he that runnes may read it: for put downe this title in the latine tongue, (which is the tongue by him aduanced aboue Greeke or Hebrew, wherein he writes his <hi>Letters,</hi> giues his <hi>lawes</hi> and his <hi>Bulls,</hi> and workes all his feates) and it containes the number of the beaſt, and neither more nor leſſe.</p>
               <p>GENERALIS VICARIVS DEI. 50.1. 5.1.100. 1.5. 500. 1. IN TERRIS. 1. 1.</p>
               <p>50. 1. 5. 1. 100. 1. 5. 500. 1. 1. 1. totall 666.</p>
               <p>Thus its cleer, that as the Pope will needes be Gods generall Vicar on earth, ſo he cannot haue it, but he muſt beare the marke and number of the beaſt. If a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man ſay he calls not himſelfe Gods Vicar, but
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:14313:42"/> Chriſts Vicar, I anſwere Chriſt is both God &amp; man, and he holdes himſelfe Chriſts Vicar, euen as Chriſt is God, and full little would he thanke him that holds him Chriſts Vicar, onely as he is a man: But I anſwer further, that who euer reads his owne decrees &amp; pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like conſtitutions, ſhall eaſily ſee that he calls himſelfe ordinarily the Vicar of God, and ſuffers others ſo to ſtile him: and that the world may ſee they haue not reformed it,<note place="margin">Tuccii Tuccii patritii lucen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis &amp; protonet Apoſtol: com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in cant. lug. <hi>606. 4.</hi> In titulo libr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> the Pope that now is, <hi>Paul the</hi> 5. hath ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered one of his owne creatures in a booke dedicated to him, to call him <hi>the Vicar of God.</hi> Thus he will needs be Gods vicar, but his pride is well paid for, for as he will be <hi>Gods Vicar</hi> againſt Gods will, ſo God makes him beare the diuels marke, in the number of the beaſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his owne will.</p>
               <p>If therefore it be ſo likely that <hi>Rome is Babylon,</hi> and her doctrines and deceits, ſuperſtitions, and Idolatryes, the fornications of that <hi>whore of Babylon,</hi> then we eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beleeue this to be true, that <hi>oft times did Babylon allure him with her entiſements,</hi> and wooe him to her ſpirituall fornications: ſo hath ſhe done many more, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailes with too many.</p>
               <p>But what, with him? No, he wil haue none: it is wel ſaid. Oh that you would do as well, that is the worſt we wiſh you <hi>Ieſuits,</hi> though you wiſh vs nothing but fire and gunpowder: oh that you would turne into your ſelues and ſee your error in beleeuing her, and in being deceiued with her inchantments, and <hi>dronk with her fornications</hi> that you would no longer be the ſonnes of her that is the <hi>mother of abhominations</hi> leaſt
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:14313:42"/> you be alſo children of abhomination: oh that you would <hi>forſake her and diſcouer her ſkirts, and teare her in pieces</hi> as ſhe hath deſerued, and then returne to be the children of the Church, &amp; ſeruants of the liuing God! this is that we wiſh you from the Lord, whome we al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo pray that thou whoſoeuer thou art, that wrote this and all other of thy faction in the worlde, may haue grace to performe that which heere thou promiſeſt.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>No no, though heauen and hell ſhould meete Ile none,</l>
                  <l>Ile none vngratious ſtrumpet, get thee gone.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Well then, if he will haue none of <hi>Babilons</hi> dainties what will he haue? for he ſaith he thirſteth, and muſt haue his thirſt quenched, but how?</p>
               <q>Quench me with blood ſweete ſonne, with milk good mother</q>
               <p>But alas theſe are children of Babilon, they wil not be healed: for loe he ſings his olde ſong againe, he muſt haue <hi>blood,</hi> he muſt haue <hi>milke:</hi> loe heere the <hi>hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and thirſt</hi> of a papiſt, it is for <hi>milke</hi> as well as <hi>blood:</hi> our Sauiour proclaymeth to the world,<note place="margin">Math 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Bleſſed are they that hunger and thirſt after righteouſnes,</hi> I would heere aske a reaſonable papiſt, a briefe queſtion, whether this righteouſnes can be attained by any meanes, but by the <hi>blood</hi> of the Mediator: If he thinke it may, let him that ſaith ſo, take time to conſider of it, and he wil anſwere otherwiſe: But if not (as if they be Chriſtians they muſt needes anſwere) then what a kinde of thirſt is that, that thirſteth for the <hi>milke</hi> of a creature, as wel as for the <hi>blood</hi> of the Mediator: But whilſt they take time to anſwere this queſtion, let vs goe forward, and trace this Ieſuit to his vnhappy iourneyes end.</p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:14313:43"/>
                  <l>dic matri meus his frater ſitit optima mater</l>
                  <l>Vi de fonte <hi>tuo</hi> promere, deque <hi>meo?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Dicnato, meus his frater mi mellee fili,</l>
                  <l>Captiuus monſtra vincula, litron habes</l>
                  <l>Ergo redemptorem mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtra te iure vocari</l>
                  <l>nobilior reliquis ſi tibi <hi>ſanguis</hi> in eſt.</l>
                  <l>Tuq parens monstra matre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> te iure vocari</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vbera</hi> ſi reliquis diuitiora geris.</l>
               </q>
               <p>That is,
<q>
                     <l>Say to thy mother ſee my brothers thirſt,</l>
                     <l>Mother, your <hi>milke</hi> will eaſe him at the firſt:</l>
                     <l>Say to thy ſonne, beholde thy brothers bands,</l>
                     <l>Sweet ſonne thou haſte his ranſome in thy hands</l>
                     <l>Shew thy redeeming power to ſoules oppreſt,</l>
                     <l>Thou ſonne if that thy <hi>bloud</hi> excell the reſt:</l>
                     <l>And ſhew thy ſelfe iuſtly ſo ſtilde indeed,</l>
                     <l>Thou mother if thy <hi>breſts</hi> the reſt exceed.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Now if you pleaſe to obſerue a little, you ſhall ſee a new peece of popiſh deuotion: his ground already layd is, that he muſt haue <hi>milke</hi> from the mother: <hi>blood</hi> of the ſonne.</p>
               <p>But how will he come by them? he hath found a
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:14313:43"/> ready way, he will make the ſonne <hi>mediator</hi> to his mother, and the mother to her ſonne: <hi>Chriſtian Religion</hi> hath euer taught, that the ſonne is our Mediator to the father: and <hi>Popiſh religion</hi> hath long taught that the Mother is a Mediator to her ſonne: But now they begin to teach, that the <hi>ſonne is alſo a mediator to his mother:</hi> what will it come to in the end? And heere obſerue, that as euer heretofore when there was any honour in precedence, the <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> had the firſt place: ſo now when it is a burden and a duty, the <hi>ſonne</hi> muſt haue it, but not till then, for ſo he now ſaith.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Say to thy mother ſee thy brothers thirſt,</l>
                  <l>Mother your milke will eaſe him at the firſt.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Firſt indeed he intreates the ſonne and then the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: but what intreats he him? to be a meanes: to whome? to his mother: for what? for her <hi>milke:</hi> ſo that vpon the matter, her milke is it that is firſt in his thoughts, its that he longs for principally, and Chriſt Ieſus ſhall be preferred to goe a meſſage to his mother, and to entreat for him, that he may haue it: as tho he had ſaid, o Ieſus my ſoule ſo thirſts for <hi>milke,</hi> that I cannot be without it: now becauſe thou haſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buked me for my preſumption, in offering to take it as boldly as thy <hi>blood:</hi> I haue therefore no other way but to intreat thee to be a meanes to thy mother, that ſo by thy mediation and her mercy I may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it, therefore I beſeech thee Ieſus <hi>ſay to thy mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Is not <hi>Chriſt</hi> honoured and wel aduanced by Popery
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:14313:44"/> that makes him mediator to a woman for her <hi>milke,</hi> and for the benefits and merrits of it, and that for ſuch a one as will not be content with the benefits and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of his owne <hi>blood ſhedding:</hi> But behold good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſeriouſly what diuinity heere is! <hi>A Chriſtian man in his deuotion may</hi> (ſaith this Ieſuit) <hi>deſire Ieſus Chriſt to goe intreat his mother for him, and to complaine that his poore brothers ſoule thirſteth, deſiring her to quench and comfort him with her milke:</hi> what is this we heare? Is Chriſt a mediator to a creature? and for ſomething in that crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to quench the ſpirituall thirſt of the ſoule? If this be true, then what meant Chriſt to ſay <hi>Come vnto me all that be weary,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>and I will eaſe you:</hi> for if he ſend them that be thirſty and weary to his mother to be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, ſurely in that word, Chriſt either ſpake too much of <hi>himſelfe,</hi> or too little of his <hi>Mother.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If Chriſt held that they might come onely to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, then it appeares the <hi>Ieſuits</hi> religion and his be contrary: If he knew that they might come to <hi>her,</hi> as well as <hi>him,</hi> or to her by him, then what meant he to ſay <hi>Come vnto me,</hi> and not rather <hi>Come vnto her or vnto me:</hi> what can they, what dare they ſay? was he vndu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull to his mother? or enuied he her dignity? or <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got</hi> he her when he thus ſpake? or was he ſwayed with too much <hi>ſelfe-loue?</hi> if none of theſe without blaſphemy may be imagined, then what may be ſaid, that there were any ſuch thing due to her, and he knew it not? If this alſo be impoſſible, then there remaines but one that he named himſelfe, but <hi>excluded</hi> not his mother, he bids come to him, and forbids not to come to her:
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:14313:44"/> I anſwer, firſt heere he bids vs come to himſelfe, let them ſhew where he bids vs goe <hi>to her,</hi> if he no where bid it, it is as good as forbidden: againe, he that in <hi>one caſe</hi> of truth ſaid, <hi>I and my father are one,</hi> would not haue ſpared in <hi>this caſe</hi> if it had bene true, to haue ſayd <hi>I and my mother are one,</hi> and he who out of his holy hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, and knowing the difference of the fathers dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and his owne humanity, freely confeſſed <hi>my father is greater then I,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hn. 14.</note> would neuer haue ſcorned (if it had bene true) to haue acknowledged, <hi>my mother is as great as I:</hi> whereas contrarywiſe, leauing out her and all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in the world, he ſaith directly, <hi>Come vnto me:</hi> And whereas he came to <hi>fulfill all righteouſnes:</hi> and the fift commaundement we know commaunds aſwell reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to Parents, as obedience: therefore doubtleſſe he <hi>who went hence</hi> ſaith the text <hi>and was obedient to them,</hi> would alſo moſt readily haue yeilded her this reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce if it had bene due vnto her, or if it might lawfully haue bene giuen her: But he knowing the contrary, doth in this caſe paſſe by her, and commaunds <hi>Come vnto me:</hi> If yet they will reply and ſay he ſaith indeed come to him, but meaning to ſend vs from himſelfe to <hi>her</hi> for eaſe &amp; comfort, who is the <hi>Mother of mercy &amp; of grace:</hi> I anſwere, ſo indeed is ſhe called in their ſeruice booke,<note n="*" place="margin">Maria mater gratiae <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ter mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>e: t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> nos ab hoſte <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ge, et ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra mortes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>. Officium beat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>triae.</note> but Gods booke takes that name to himſelfe onely, &amp; giues it to no creature, therefore let them an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere it that giue it to her: Againe, the ground of this replication is falſe, for as he ſaith <hi>Come to me,</hi> and names no other, ſo neither ſends he vs <hi>to her</hi> for eaſe, but ſaith plainely and directly, <hi>and I will eaſe you.</hi>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:14313:45"/> Further, they not onely make Chriſt a mediator to his mother, and that for ſpirituall eaſe and comfort, but they doe it in ſuch a faſhion, as they make Chriſt one that either is not able or not willing to helpe vs him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: for if he were, then why doe they ſay that he complaines to his mother, that <hi>we thirſt,</hi> and for the eaſe of our ſoules, do <hi>yeeld her milke?</hi> If heere they were asked this queſtion, I wonder how they would anſwer it? if Chriſt be not <hi>willing</hi> or not <hi>able</hi> to eaſe the thirſty ſoule, then how is he a perfect Sauiour? If he be, then how is it likely that he would ſend him that humbleth his ſoule to him for helpe, to another to be eaſed, ſeeing he asketh of him, who ſaid, <hi>come vnto me all that are weary,</hi> doth he aske that that Chriſt hath to giue, and is it likely he will deny it? dooth he aske that that <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath not to giue, and is it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable that his <hi>mother</hi> hath it? then they may aſwell ſay that ſhe hath more grace and mercy, or more power &amp; ability then Chriſt himſelf hath: let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> anſwer theſe queſtions, how they will, heere will be found ſtrange diuinity, which we ſee is curra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in the Romiſh Church.</p>
               <p>But whilſt they prepare their anſwere, let it pleaſe the reader to obſerue how contrary the Romiſh doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine is to the doctrine of Chriſt and of the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <note place="margin">Iohn 14 28.</note>
                           <hi>Chriſt ſaith of himſelfe as man.</hi> My father is greater then I</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Rom ſh doctrine makes him ſay</hi> My <hi>Mother</hi> is in ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects greater then I.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <note place="margin">Iohn. 10.30</note>
                           <hi>Chriſt ſaith of himſelfe as God</hi> I and my <hi>Father</hi> are one.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Romiſh doctrine makes him ſay</hi> I and my <hi>mother</hi> are one.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> 
                           <note place="margin">Math. 11.2</note>
                           <pb n="87" facs="tcp:14313:45"/>
                           <hi>Chriſt ſaith</hi> Come to me all that are weary, I will eaſe you.</cell>
                        <cell> 
                           <hi>Romiſh doctrine makes him ſay</hi> Come to me and I will ſend you to <hi>my mother</hi> for eaſe:</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <note place="margin">1. Tim. 2.5</note>
                           <hi>The ſcripture ſaith</hi> Chriſt is the mediator be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>God and man.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Romiſh doctrine ſaith</hi> Chriſt is the mediator be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>man and Mary.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <note place="margin">Iohn. 14.6.</note>
                           <hi>The ſcripture ſaith</hi> No man commeth to the <hi>father</hi> but by me.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>They make him ſay:</hi> No man commeth to my <hi>Mother</hi> but by me:</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <note place="margin">Iohn. 15.16</note>
                           <hi>The ſcripture ſaith</hi> Whatſoeuer you aske my father in my name he will giue it you.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>They make him ſay.</hi> Whatſoeuer you aske my Mother in my name ſhe will giue it you.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe and ſuch like oppoſitions are common be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>Christs Goſpell</hi> and Romiſh diuinity, may not this giue ſtrong ſuſpition that their religion is <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian,</hi> which in the foundations of it are ſo repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to Chriſts, as theſe and others which ſtand con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed with more authority then yet theſe doe? well, thus Chriſt is made a mediator to his mother, now the Ieſuit proceedeth, and to make him amends hee makes the mother a mediator to him,
<q>
                     <l>Say to thy Sonne behold my brothers bands.</l>
                     <l>Sweete Sonne thou haſt his ranſome in thy hands.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>That Chriſt Ieſus hath the <hi>ranſome</hi> of ſinfull ſoules
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:14313:46"/> in his hands is good diuinity, and we heartily imbrace it, wiſhing it were as heartily and truly (without Equiuocation) intended, by this papiſt: if he and all other papiſts doe ſo hold it, we heartily reioyce, but then we deſire them to anſwere to a fewe queſtions.</p>
               <p>Who payeth this ranſome? is it not <hi>Chriſt?</hi> who ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts it? is it not God the <hi>father?</hi> is it not mercy, grace &amp; loue, that either the one will <hi>accept</hi> it, or the other <hi>pay</hi> it? can any pay it but the one? can any take it but the other? are not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they the fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tains &amp; fathers of mercy, which haue done ſo? if all theſe be true, then what a religion haue they, who in their liturgies &amp; daily prayers, call a creature the <hi>mother of mercy, and mother of grace,</hi> oftner then either God the father, or Chriſt the redeemer, or both put together<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> we deſire ſome conſcionable papiſt to anſwere vs ſeriouſly: was the virgin Mary a Creator or a creature? if a creature, was ſhe any more then an excellent creature, ſet apart for the moſt excellent vſe in the world? &amp; was it not in Gods election to haue choſen any other woman, at his owne good pleaſure to haue bene the mother of Chriſt? and was it not his owne free mercy, that <hi>he regarded the low eſtate of her his handmaid?</hi> if this be ſo, then did ſhe anything in our ſaluation, which any woman had not done, if God had taken her to be his mother: was there any thing in her to moue God to chuſe her, which was not Gods owne gift in her and to her? ſhe may be then a veſſell of grace but ſhe can be no way a fountaine of grace: for what had ſhe but ſhe receiued it: but if (as they ſay) ſhe be the fountaine of mercy and mother of grace, then ſhe
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:14313:46"/> giues but receiues not, as the fountaine receiues from no other, but hath of it ſelfe, and ſends out to others: &amp; the mother takes not of her children, but layeth vp for them. Now if it be as their liturgie ſaith, it is that ſhe is the mother of mercy and grace, &amp;c. as aboue: of grace and mercy, then ſure <hi>ſhe hath the ranſome in her hands:</hi> but if it be <hi>in Chriſts hands,</hi> as heere they ſay it is, then how is ſhe the mother of mercy? hardly would theſe be reconciled, but that they haue equiuocations, reſeruations, or deſtinctions, that will make any thing ſeeme good inough to ſerue their turnes.</p>
               <p>Thus then they haue not onely made Mary Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor to Chriſt, which is common in their religion, but (which was ſcarce euer heard of before) they make <hi>Chriſt</hi> their mediator to <hi>her,</hi> her to him for his <hi>blood,</hi> but firſt him to her for her <hi>milke:</hi> now to leaue this point, obſerue (in one word) how in theſe two meſſages of mediation, here is no difference, but ſhe that is a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and ſaued by her ſonne, is made to ſpeake to him in the ſame tearmes as he to her, and with no other words or ſignes of reuerence: and he her ſonne and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, yea God himſelfe made to ſpeake to her with the ſame reuerence as ſhe doth to him: as thogh there were no difference betwixt <hi>him</hi> and <hi>her,</hi> and as though he being God and her ſauiour, was aſmuch beholding to her for her <hi>milke,</hi> as ſhe being a creature is to him for his <hi>blood:</hi> Loe what popiſh deuotion is heere? now if they be aſhamed of this, then why are they not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of the other? But they are farre from that, for
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:14313:47"/> where are the intreatings, the cries, the humble re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts and ſubmiſſiue beſeechings to him for his <hi>blood?</hi> heere be none ſuch: but contrariwiſe as though there were no difference in the world, betwixt either the perſons entreating, which are <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>Mary,</hi> or the things deſired which be his <hi>blood</hi> &amp; her <hi>milke,</hi> he ſaith to Chriſt.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Say to thy mother ſee my brothers thirſt,</l>
                  <l>Mother your milke will help him at the firſt.</l>
               </q>
               <p>And to her he ſaith,
<q>
                     <l>Say to thy ſonne behold thy brothers bands,</l>
                     <l>Sweete ſonne thou haſt his ranſome in thy hands:</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Thus Popery makes of <hi>Chriſt and Mary,</hi> one no grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a perſon then the other, and of his <hi>blood</hi> and her <hi>milke</hi> one, no greater a matter then the other: <hi>Chriſt</hi> with no more reuerence to be implored then <hi>Mary,</hi> his <hi>blood</hi> with no more vehemency to be deſired, with no more difficulty to be obtayned then her <hi>milke:</hi> If this doctrine may be defended vnder pretence of deuoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, then will not there want a cullour for any blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my: But the Ieſuit goeth forward and ſaith to Chriſt.</p>
               <q> Ergo redemptorem monstra<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp;c.</q>
               <q>
                  <l>Shew thy redeeming power to ſoules oppreſt,</l>
                  <l>Thou ſonne of that thy <hi>bloud</hi> excells the reſt.</l>
                  <l>And ſhewe thy ſelfe iuſtly ſo ſtilde indeede,</l>
                  <l>Thou mother, if thy <hi>breſts</hi> the reſt exceede.</l> 
               </q>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:14313:47"/>
               <p>It may be doubted in whoſe name he ſpeaketh theſe words, whether in <hi>his owne,</hi> to both Chriſt &amp; his mother, or in <hi>Chriſts</hi> name to his mother, and in hers to him: if in the firſt, they containe <hi>blaſphemy,</hi> if in the ſecond, <hi>abſurdity:</hi> for if he ſuppoſe the virgin <hi>Mary</hi> ſaith thus to Chriſt,
<q>
                     <l>Shew thy redeeming power to ſoules oppreſt,</l>
                     <l>Thou ſonne if that thy blood excell the reſt.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>It is fouly abſurd to imagine that ſhe being ſo dignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as ſhe is (yea rather as they hold<note place="margin">Horatius. T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſellinus Ieſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in hiſtor. lau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tanae in praf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> almoſt deified) ſhould make an if, or a queſtion whether Chriſts blood excell the reſt or no: and much more abſurd is it to make Chriſt ſeeme to be ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of his mothers power and ſtate how great it is: be it more or leſſe. But if ſo be he ſpeak theſe words himſelfe to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both, then behold the haynous iniury done to the pretious <hi>blood</hi> of the mediator. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning which this wicked papiſt makes as much &amp; equall doubt, whether it excell the <hi>blood</hi> of other creatures, as he doth: whether the <hi>milke</hi> of the Vrgin <hi>Mary</hi> excel the milke of all other women: let all chriſtian men ſhrinke and tremble at ſo great a blaſphemy, for al the learned Papiſts in the world may be challe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dged to proue (if they can) out of Gods word &amp; the grounds of Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that ſhe was any more then another holy woman, (ſauing this prerogatiue, that ſhe was his mother acording to the fleſh) or any more then a Saint of God ſanctified by the ſpirit, and ſaued by the <hi>blood</hi> of Ieſus chriſt, whoſe mother ſhe was in regard of his fleſh: or that her milke had any vertue in the world, but to nouriſh his body as doth the milke
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:14313:48"/> of other women, their children: for was not he <hi>a man like vnto vs in all things (ſinne excepted)</hi> and if Chriſt take it no preiudice to himſelfe, to be like <hi>vnto men,</hi> ſhall it be a wrong to her to be like to other <hi>women?</hi> Nay we dare goe further and aske them, if God haue vouchſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed once in the whole new teſtament, ſo much as to name the milke of the virgin Mary? whereas altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and almoſt in euery chapter, he extolleth the <hi>blood</hi> of Chriſt, and is euer magnifying the vertue, merrits, and efficacy of the ſame: if this be ſo, then what ſhall we ſay to that religion and to thoſe men, who make it as queſtionable, whether Chriſt Ieſus his <hi>blood</hi> excell the <hi>blood</hi> of other men, as whether the virgin Maries <hi>milke</hi> exceed the <hi>milke</hi> of other women? is this Romiſh religion? is this popiſh diuinity? then ſee what follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. But it cannot be proued either to <hi>reaſon</hi> or to <hi>faith</hi> that her <hi>milke</hi> excelleth other womens, in any ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all or corporall vertue or operation: therefore it is not to be proued that Chriſts <hi>blood</hi> is more pretious then other mens: ſee here my deere countrymen, how you are miſled, ſee what doctrine you are fed withall by your teachers! open your eyes and be no longer deceiued; offer not this iniury to him that gaue his life for you, to make this vnequall compariſon: If they wil not teach you holy and found diuinity, then leaue them, and learne from vs, or rather with vs from the holy ſcriptures, that <hi>his blood is the price of our redemptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> but as for her milke we know no ſuch thing, ſince ſhe liued on the earth: acknowledge with vs that it is a fundamentall ground of Chriſtian faith that his <hi>blood</hi>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:14313:48"/> is more worth then ten worlds: but that her <hi>milke</hi> is now of any vallue, can neither be perſwaded to <hi>reaſon</hi> nor belieued by <hi>faith:</hi> and yet dar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this malignant ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue make that as likely as probable, as certaine as the other: If enemies of Religion take hold heere, and ſay, that therefore the grounds of our Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity are vncertaine, and ſo blaſpheme the bleſſed blood of our Sauiour, we can ſay no more but our Church is innocent, our hearts are free, our hands are cleere of it: <hi>woe be to them by whome the offence commeth.</hi> But now let vs ſee how the Ieſuit concludes, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his end be any better then his beginning.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>O quando lactabor ab vbere, vulnere paſcar!</l>
                  <l>delitiis<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> fruar, ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma, latuſque tuis!</l>
                  <l>Parce Deus, magno ſi te clamore fatigem:</l>
                  <l>non potis imperio, non poti arte regi,</l>
                  <l>Exagitante ſiti, Patientia perdit habenas</l>
                  <l>clamores ſi vis tollere, tolle ſitim.</l>
                  <l>Pluris ego clauis: ſaturaſti ſanguine clauos</l>
                  <l>lanceaque erubu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t ſanguine tincta tuo.</l>
                  <l>pluris ego pannis: madueru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vndique panni</l>
                  <l>nati a vulneribus, Matris ab vberibus.</l>
               </q>
               <p>In Engliſh thus:
<q>
                     <pb n="94" facs="tcp:14313:49"/>
                     <l>Ah when ſhall I with theſe be ſatiſfied,</l>
                     <l>when ſhall I ſwimme in ioyes of breſt and ſide:</l>
                     <l>Pardon O God mine eager earneſtneſſe,</l>
                     <l>if I thy lawes and reaſons bounds tranſgreſſe,</l>
                     <l>Where thirſt ore-ſwaies, Patience is thruſt away:</l>
                     <l>ſtay but my thirſt and then my cries will ſtay,</l>
                     <l>Better am I then nailes, yet did a ſtreame</l>
                     <l>of thy deere <hi>bloud</hi> waſh both the Launce &amp; them:</l>
                     <l>More worthy I then clouts, yet them a floude</l>
                     <l>moyſtned of Mothers <hi>milke</hi> &amp; of Sonnes <hi>blood.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Now comes to his concluſion, but alas his iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is as much at the laſt as at the firſt: for ſtill he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in his impiety, without repentance, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morce, without ſorrow or ſence of the euill he hath done, for ſtill he ſings his olde ſong:
<q>O when ſhall I ſucke the milke of theſe breſts, when ſhall I drinke the blood of theſe wounds.</q>
               </p>
               <p>His ſoule thirſteth, but for what? for <hi>milke</hi> and for <hi>blood:</hi> but firſt for <hi>milke</hi> and then for <hi>blood:</hi> If this be tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable diuinity, nay if this be holy deuotion, then what did our bleſſed Sauiour meane to cry out to all weary and thirſty ſoules, <hi>If any man thirſt let him come vnto me and drinke:</hi> I wiſh the Ieſuits would tell vs what they thinke, whether he did well or no, to leaue out the Virgin Mary: for if this diuinity of theirs be good, then he ought to haue ſaid, <hi>If any man thirſt let him come to my mother or to me to drinke:</hi> and ſurely if her
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:14313:49"/> milke be thus equall in value, price and merrit to his blood, then we do no longer maruell that they teach how the Virgin Mary did riſe from the dead, and was aſſumed into heauen corporally that as Chriſt roſe &amp; aſcended to apply &amp; make good the merit of his death, ſo did ſhe alſo to make effectual the merit of her milk. But then good <hi>Paul</hi> how farre art thou to blame, that eſteemd all things in the world, doug, and droſſe, &amp; only that thou maiſt know the vertue of his reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on! for then it ſeemes, thou wilt giue little or nothing to know the vertue of her aſſumption. Nay it may be thou art halfe an hereticke, and beleeueſt not any ſuch aſſumption: but if thou couldeſt be taken within the reach of the holy inquiſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, thou ſhouldeſt pay wel for ſuch thy hereticall incredulity. If now thou wert aliue thy better and more holy bretheren the Ieſuits, could reproue thee for many indiſcreet paſſages, and teach thee better diuinity then thou ſeemeſt to know, for whereas thou durſt ſay, <hi>thou eſteemdſt to know nothing but Ieſus Chriſt, and him crucified,</hi> they can tell thee thou art farre ſhort in thy duty, and but cold in zeale in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of them, for they ſtand in doubt whether to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme more the blood of his wounds, or the milke of her paps: and whereas thou wilt giue all to <hi>knowe the vertue of his reſurrection,</hi> they can but wonder at thy ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, who careſt not to know the vertue of her re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection &amp; aſcention alſo, Be thou content to know the one, they for their parts will know both: and if thou be ſo preciſe for thy Maiſter, that thou canſt not be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent to ſay, that <hi>he purgeth our ſins,</hi> but muſt exclude
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:14313:50"/> al other, and ſay, that he <hi>by himſelfe</hi> purgeth our ſinnes: know thou that they dare be ſo bold as to put out that word <hi>by himſelfe</hi> out of the text: and when they read thy Epiſtles they are halfe aſhamed to ſee what a bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy man thou art, for thou art all in <hi>blood, blood,</hi> inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as twenty times at leaſt thou art ſtil vpon blood as though there were no ſaluation but by blood, and as though bleſſed Maries milke had no merit at all. It ſeemes that as thou wert a perſecutor, and deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in blood afore thy conuerſion, ſo thou beares ſtil a bloody minde: but now behold theſe meek, &amp; milde and merciful men (the Ieſuits,) a generation that loues no cruelty, nor ſeekes to ſhed no blood (as moſt nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the world can wel beare witneſſe<note n="*" place="margin">Witneſſe in England the Powder trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: In France the laſt Kings death: the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent warres in Sweden and broyles in Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, &amp;c.</note>) theſe ſweet and gratious fathers being poſſeſſed with a better ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, are weary of blood and do rather chooſe and deſire milke to quench the ſpiriuall thirſt of their ſoules.</p>
               <p>If they would vtter what their prophane hearts thinke, or diſcouer openly what they mutter amongſt themſelues, we ſhould heare them publiſh euen ſuch diuinity as this is: a taſte whereof beſides the preſent poems, you ſhall read anon.</p>
               <p>But now for his concluſion, this blaſpheming Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit dare proceed and turne his ſpeech to God, and not fearing the commaundement that forbids him to take Gods name in vaine, vnder paine of ſtanding guilty, at the barre of Gods iuſtice, he dare offer to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe the name of God, with ſuch a prayer as this.</p>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:14313:50"/>
               <p>O Lord thou muſt pardon me though I cry aloud, for it is not blood wil ſerue my ſoule, I long for milke, and am ſo a thirſt, that I may not keepe ſilence: and why Lord ſhouldeſt thou ſo long keepe me a Petitioner in this caſe? I am bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then the nayles, yet they had blood inough: I am not ſo vilde as cloutes, yet they wanted nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther milke nor blood.</p>
               <p>Wat kinde of men are theſe Ieſuits, or what a God is their God, to whome they dare preſent ſuch a prayer as this? ſurely they thinke as baſely of him as they doe highly of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, or elſe they neuer durſt thus inſult ouer him, &amp; thus abuſe him, as after he hath told him plainely that <hi>his blood is drinke indeede,</hi> and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded <hi>them that are athirſt, to come and drinke of that well of water of life,</hi> to come and tell him to his face that their ſoules thirſt for milke, and they muſt haue it? belike theſe crawling frogs thinke that they haue ſuch a God as they may leape and play vpon at their pleaſure: But O <hi>thou that dwelleſt in heauen laugh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſcorne, haue them and their wickednes in deriſion:</hi> and ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther work them to repentance and viſible conuerſion, or bring them to vengeance and iuſt confuſion.</p>
               <p>The Ieſuit concludes with a compariſon of himſelf to the nailes and launce that pierced Chriſts bleſſed body, and the cloathes that toucht him in his infancy and death: &amp; indeed the firſt compariſon is not much vnequall, for the Ieſuits are moſt like to nailes &amp; laun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in Chriſts body; for ſeeing the holy Ghoſt tells vs
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:14313:51"/> that wicked men by their ſinnes did and do pierce Chriſt: then the Ieſuits who by their Atheiſmes, cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elties, periuries, equiuocations, treaſons, haue beene ſharper nailes and launces in Chriſts body, and grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter diſhonourers of his religion, then any other ſort of men, (if the voyce of all Chriſtendome, &amp; the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of their owne bretheren be true) then the Ieſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>its I ſay are not vnfitly reſembled to nayles and laun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: and indeed they that are thornes in the eyes, and pricks in the ſide of all princes and ſtates where they come: leſſe maruell though they be like the nailes and ſpeare in Chriſts body! therefore let the Ieſuit pleaſe himſelfe in this compariſon, as long as he will, we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy it not.</p>
               <p>But for the ſecond, that he is better then the clothes that were about thoſe two bleſſed bodies, I ſay but this: that either the Ieſuits are farre more holy then the Prophet Eſay, or els he farre more humble in his owne eyes then they: for he profeſſeth in his own &amp; the churches name, that they were no better the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the filthieſt cloute that euer was, <hi>euen a menſtruous cloth.</hi> But ſaith the Ieſuit, I am better then the beſt cloth that euer was, for though we holde that God hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen laſting vertue to his word and ſacraments, but none that we know to rags, or clouts: yet we acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that as farre as clothes may one excell another, thoſe that touched the bodies of our Lord &amp; his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, are the moſt pretious, and if we could be ſure we had them, we would eſteeme them aboue cloth of gold: we therefore wonder how a man comming be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:14313:51"/> the Lord his God, dare in his prayer make himſelf better then thoſe clothes, eſpecially hearing the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet cry before him, O Lord al our righteouſnes is like a menſtruouſe clout. If our beſt be ſo filthy, what is our nature, what is our ſin? if he anſwer that this is but a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, for he meanes that being a man he is therfore ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of grace &amp; ſaluation, which the clothes are not, I thinke ſo alſo: But then why doth he enuy that milke and blood ſhould touch them? If he meane the mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall and reall <hi>milke</hi> and <hi>blood</hi> that were in the bodies of Chriſt and his mother, then he is more then mad, to enuy the nayles, the launce, the cloutes, for they did touch them, and yet he cannot, and if he complaine that he may not, we aske him why then did not the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles take more carefull order to gather vp and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue that <hi>milke</hi> and <hi>blood,</hi> or if they did not, at leaſt why did they not complaine of the want of them, as he doth heere? ſurely either they had too little <hi>deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> or the Ieſuits too much <hi>ſuperſtition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But if he meane the vertue, merite and efficacy of the <hi>blood</hi> &amp; <hi>milkë,</hi> then let him anſwer vs two ſhort queſtions: Firſt, what ſpiritual vertue and power had that <hi>milke,</hi> what did it worke in our ſaluation, (more then the <hi>milke</hi> of another woman coulde) what did it merit for vs? what the <hi>blood</hi> did we knowe and moſt willingly acknowledge: but what the <hi>milke</hi> did or can doe, if the Ieſuites can tell and teache vs, we will not refuſe to learne: But ſuppoſing that it had much ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue as the <hi>blood</hi> (as the Ieſuite affirmes, but farre be it from vs once ſo to thinke) then ſecondly wee aske
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:14313:52"/> him doth he thinke the nayles, launce, &amp; cloutes were partakers of the vertue and merrit of that <hi>blood,</hi> if he doe, let him ſhew where he receiued ſuch diuinity: if not, then to what end complaines he to God in ſuch a faſhion.</p>
               <p>Lord I am better then the nayles and cloutes, and yet they had blood and milke inough, but I dye for thirſt.</p>
               <p>If this be not to take Gods name in vaine, and that in a high meaſure, we appeale to all Chriſtian men of reaſonable iudgement.</p>
               <p>And thus at laſt are we come to an end of this Ieſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iticall Goſpell, the impiety whereof I now remit to the cenſure of the Chriſtian world:</p>
               <p>And for my concluſion, leaſt any ſhould ſay that this is but one priuate Ieſuits deede, and therfore may not preiudice the whole ſociety of Ieſuits, and much leſſe the religion of Popery.</p>
               <p>To theſe I anſwere, the booke is allowed and hath bene twiſe printed, and ſtands approued by <hi>Poſſeuine,</hi> amongſt good and catholike authors. 2. Shew what Ieſuit or other popiſh doctor hath <hi>reproued,</hi> or what Inquiſitor or other popiſh magiſtrate hath <hi>cenſured</hi> this wickedneſſe. 3. Which is worſt of all, It is no more in effect then others of them haue taught or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued, though not in ſo open &amp; apparant a faſhion: But let any Chriſtian man iudge what diuinity is laide downe in theſe points that follow.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Papiſts haue a booke called the <hi>Mariale,</hi> It hath
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:14313:52"/> bene obiected vnto them that in that booke it is thus ſaid: Salomon ſaith, <hi>the name of the Lord is a ſtrong tower,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">This hath bene long a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe laid to their charge in <hi>Catalogo, te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtium veritati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> edit toais</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>08</note> Prou 18.10. But Salomon knew little of the Virgin Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry let vs therfore ſay, <hi>the name of our lady is a ſtrong tower,</hi> let the ſinner flye vnto her, and he ſhall be ſaued: and againe: thou art a ſinner, flye then to the name of Mary, that alone ſhall ſerue to heale thee: and againe,</p>
               <p>The Lord was with Mary, and Mary with the Lord in the ſame labour and ſame work of our redemption for the Mother of mercy helped the father of mercy, in the worke of our ſaluation: and therevpon was it ſpoken of the firſt woman, <hi>It is not good for man to be alone, let vs make him a helper:</hi> But why then ſaith God, Eſay 63 <hi>I haue troden the wine preſſe alone, and of all people, there was no man with me:</hi> the booke anſwereth, It is true Lord that thou ſayeſt, there was no man with thee: but there was a woman with thee, which bore all the wounds in her heart, that thou didſt beare in thy body.</p>
               <p>Loe heere a peece of rare diuinity! Salomon is blamed for ignorance, that he knew but little of the Virgin, &amp; in a ſort is rebuked for ſaying <hi>the name of our Lord,</hi> and not rather the name of our Lady <hi>is a ſtrong tower:</hi> and though no man did, yet a woman (namely Mary) did helpe Chriſt to tread the winepreſſe of Gods wrath, and was fellow worker with God, in the worke of our redemption.</p>
               <p>This booke ſtands vnconfuted, vncondemned, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reproued, by the Ieſuits or the Romiſh Church, till this day, for ought that I can yet find, yet hath it bene
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:14313:53"/> many yeares laid to their charge.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Againe, the Papiſts haue a booke, they call our La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies pſalter,<note place="margin">Vide Pſalte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ium beate Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s Mariae: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mpreſsum cum Pſalterio Cu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tercienfi, Par. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rca an. <hi>1520</hi> Extat etiam i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem Pſalteriu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d verbum. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud Chemniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, in Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine concil Tri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dent: in parte <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. pag. <hi>149.</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diti onts franco furt. <hi>1596.</hi>
                  </note> printed at Paris in the yeare 1520. or thereabouts, wherein euery one of the 150. pſalmes are in whole or in part turned from <hi>Dominus</hi> to <hi>Domina,</hi> that is from God or Chriſt, to our Lady, as In the firſt pſalme.</p>
               <p>Bleſſed is the man that loueth thy name O Virgin Mary, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>In the 19 Pſalme.</p>
               <p>The heauens declare thy glory O Virgin Mary &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In the</hi> 29 <hi>Pſalme,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Bring vnto our Lady O you mighty, bring vnto our Lady worſhip and honour &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In the</hi> 51. <hi>Pſalme,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Haue mercy vpon me O Lady, thou that art called the Mother of mercy, and according to the bowels of thy mercyes, cleanſe me from all my ſinnes, poure out thy grace vpon me, and take not thy wonted mercy from me, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In the</hi> 57 <hi>pſalme.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Haue mercy vpon me O Lady, haue mercy vpon me, for my heart is ready to ſearch out thy will, and in the ſhadow of thy wings will I reſt &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In the</hi> 68. <hi>pſalme.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let our Lady ariſe and her enemies ſhall be ſcattered, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In the</hi> 72 <hi>Pſalme.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Lord giue thy iudgement to the King, and thy mercy to our Lady his mother.</p>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:14313:53"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>In the</hi> 94 <hi>Pſalme.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>God is the God of reuenge, but thou O Lady the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of mercy, doſt bowe him to take pitty &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In the</hi> 96 <hi>Pſalme.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O ſing vnto our Lady a new ſong for ſhe hath done maruailous thinges, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In the</hi> 110 <hi>Pſalme.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Lord ſaid vnto our Lady, Sit thou mother at my right hand &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Thus I might goe ouer all the Pſalmes, but as he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan he ends in the laſt words of the laſt Pſalme.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Let euery thing that hath breath praiſe our Lady.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now this booke ſtands not onely vncontrolled,<note place="margin">Gregor. de Va<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in vol, de reb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> fidei controuer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſis, ſect. <hi>5.</hi> lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Idolotria cap. <hi>10.</hi> Bernardinus de Buſtis, in Marials part <hi>3.</hi> ſer. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> but rather euen defended by the Ieſuits, and thoſe of the principall.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Againe, a famous Fryer &amp; well approued amongſt them, preacht this doctrine in the pulpit (amongſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other, little better.)</p>
               <p>A man may appeale from God himſelfe to the Virgin Mary, If any Man feele himſelfe agrieued at the iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of God, ſeeing God hath deuided his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome with her, for whereas God hath Iuſtice and mercy, he hath reſerued Iuſtice to himſelfe, to be exerciſed in this world as it pleaſeth him: but Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy he hath committed to his mother: If therefore any man finde himſelfe agrieued in the Court of Gods Iuſtice, let him appeale to the Court of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, of his mother.</p>
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:14313:54"/>
               <p>This diuinity was ſo well reliſht in the Romiſh Church, that after he had preacht it, he publiſht it vnder the Popes owne Patronage: and the booke was againe printed within theſe three yeares: but what ſay the Ieſuits to it, they teſtifie that this booke is a learned and godly booke, full of goodneſſe and piety.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, <hi>Horatius Turſellinus</hi> himſelfe, a Ieſuit of good eſteeme amongſt them,<note place="margin">Horatius Tur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ellinus: in Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>toria virg. lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tanae in prefat</note> writes thus,</p>
               <p>Almighty God hath made the Virgin his mother, as farre as he may lawfully, partaker of his diuine pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Maieſty.</p>
               <p>Now ſurely if God haue made her fellow with him of his diuine maieſty, leſſe maruel if Chriſt haue made her fellow in the worke of redemption.<note place="margin">Poſseuinus in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>it H.</note> And this booke written by a Ieſuit, hath publike allowance, and is dedicated to Cardinall <hi>Aldobrandino.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fiftly, a great Spaniſh Doctor, and profeſſor of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinity of his order, writes thus.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn. Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oſtomus a viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>atione, de ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tis domine to <hi>2</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ib. <hi>2</hi> cap. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note>We haue often ſeene and heard of very many, who in their extreame dangers haue called vpon Mary, and preſently were deliuered: for oft times ſafety is ſooner obtained by calling vpon the name of Mary, then by calling vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the name of Ieſus Chriſt the ſonne of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Poſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>inus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> apparatu <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>icro lit. l</note>And this booke is both dedicated to Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the 8. &amp; receiues publike allowa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce by the Ieſuits: his name is <hi>Chriſoſtome,</hi> as tho he were a golden mouthed ſpeaker: but if this be his doctrine, that her mediation is as powerfull, or rather more then is her ſonnes, it is pitty but he ſhould be calld and accounted a <hi>leaden</hi>
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:14313:54"/> mouthed wretch:</p>
               <p>By all theſe &amp; many more that (as the learned know) might eaſily be produced, it may appere that this blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheming Ieſuit <hi>Bonarſcius,</hi> in this his deteſtable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon, of her milk with Chriſts blood, ſaith no more in effect then others both of his religion &amp; perticular ſect, and therefore it may be iuſtly concluded, this is the doctrine and diuinity not of him alone, but of the Ieſuits, and of the popiſh Church it ſelfe, as long as it ſtands approued or vncondemned by them: Now then if this be the diuinity of the Romiſh Church.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That a Creatures milke may be mingled with Chriſts blood in the matter &amp; merit of our ſaluation.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That it helpes and heales ſpirituall ſores of the ſoule as well as the blood.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That though no man did, yet a woman did help God in the worke of our ſaluation.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That the Pſalmes may be turned from Lord to Lady.</p>
               <p n="5">5. That a man may appeale from God to the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin Mary.</p>
               <p n="6">6. That God hath deuided his kingdome with her, keeping Iuſtice to himſelfe, and ſurrendring Mercy to her.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:14313:55"/>7. That God hath made her pertaker with himſelfe of his diuine power and Maieſty.</p>
               <p n="8">8. That a mans prayers are often heard, rather by and through her, then Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
               <p>If theſe I ſay be the doctrines of the preſent Church of Rome, then let the Chriſtian world be pleaſed to obſerue,</p>
               <p n="1">1. How farre the preſent Romiſh Church, is degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from the antient.</p>
               <p n="2">2. How great cauſe we and al Churches of God haue to ſeperate from ſuch a ſinagogue.</p>
               <p n="3">3. How iuſtly they may be pronounced Antichriſtian, who thus hainouſly diſparage the perſon and office of the Mediator.</p>
               <p n="4">4. How vntrue it is that by many is ſuggeſted that the preſent religion of Rome is much reformed &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined at this day: for it is moſt certaine, in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times theſe would haue beene condemned as blaſphemies euen in the Romiſh Church it ſelfe.</p>
               <p>And laſtly you of this moſt Honorable and reuerend aſſembly of the church &amp; Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon-wealth of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land may here ſee what cauſe there is to pronounce the true Papiſts <hi>Hereticks,</hi> conſidering the preſent
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:14313:55"/> Church holds not onely theſe but many other fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall errors, both for matter of faith, and of gouernement, which are perticularized in my E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle.</p>
               <p>And conſidering that all meanes haue beene vſed, to reclaime and reforme her, but all is in vaine, (for ſhe is that <hi>Babilon that will not be healed:</hi> wherefore it is our duty to forſake her and leaue her to the iuſt hand of God.</p>
               <p>Thus ſhall we follow the counſell of the Prophet in the like caſe, who ſaith: <hi>we would haue healed Babylon but ſhe vvould not be healed: let vs forſake her and goe euery man to his owne Countrey, for her Iudgement is come vp to heauen and lifted vp to the cloudes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
